Chronology

Ottoman Period

1261–1310 Foundation of ghazi principalities, including that of Ottoman.

1326 Ottoman conquest of Bursa.

1327 First Ottoman silver coin [akçe] printed in Bursa.

1352 Orhan grants capitulations to the Genoese.

1361 Murat I conquers Adrianople (Edirne).

1385 Ottoman conquest of Sofia.

1389 Battle of Kosovo fought; Ottomans emerge victorious, but Murat I is slain.

1394–1402 Ottoman blockade of Constantinople.

1402 Battle of Ankara waged; Timur captures Bayezit I.

1413 Mehmet I unifies Ottoman territories.

1424 Peace treaty signed between Ottomans and Byzantines.

1453 Siege of Constantinople; fall of Pera.

1460 Conquest of the Morea.

1475 Ottoman suzerainty over the khanate of the Crimea.

1475 Battle of Çaldıran fought; Selim I defeats Shah Ismail.

1516–1517 Syria and Egypt taken.

1521 Belgrade falls.

1595–1610 Celali revolts.

1669 Crete falls.

1683 Second siege of Vienna.

1699 Treaty of Karlowitz signed.

1711 Peter the Great defeated.

1715 Morea retaken.

1718–1730 Tulip Period.

1736–1739 Belgrade retaken.

1765–1774 War with Russian Federation fought.

1774 Treaty of Küçük Kaynarca signed.

1789–1807 Era of reforms initiated by Selim III.

1826 Greece proclaims independence.

1839 Gülhane Imperial Rescript; beginning of the Tanzimat (Reform) period.

1854–1856 Crimean War waged.

1856 Reform Edict proclaimed.

1858 Land Code enacted.

1859 Ambassador sent to United States.

1867 First Ottoman sultan (Abdülaziz) visits Europe.

1876 Proclamation of the First Constitutional Period.

1878 Parliament prorogued indefinitely.

1900 Istanbul University opens.

1908 Second Constitutional Period begins. Liberal Union formed.

1909 Abdülhamit II deposed.

1911 Freedom and Accord Party established.

1912–1913 First Balkan War fought.

1913 Committee for Union and Progress in power. Second Balkan War fought.

1914 Ottomans enter World War I on the side of the Axis powers.

1918 Mudros Armistice signed.

War of Independence and Its Aftermath

1919 19 May: Mustafa Kemal lands in Samsun to start the national liberation movement. 22 June: Amasya Circular Letter circulated. 23 July–7 August: Erzurum Congress convened. 4–11 September: Sivas Congress in place.

1920 19 February: National Pact signed. 16 March: Istanbul falls under Allied military control. 23 April: Grand National Assembly convenes. 22 June: Greek army advances against Nationalists. 10 August: Treaty of Sèvres signed, parceling Turkey among the Allied powers.

1921 20 January: Constitutional Act enacted. 16 March: Treaty of Moscow signed with Soviet Union.

1922 30 August: Decisive victory won over invading Greek forces. 11 October: Mudanya Armistice signed. 1 November: Sultanate abolished.

1923 17 February: İzmir Economic Congress convened. 24 July: Lausanne Treaty essentially determines Turkey’s present boundaries. 9 August: People’s Party founded, to become the Republican People’s Party on 10 November 1924. 23 October: Ankara becomes capital city.

The First Republic of Turkey

1923 29 October: Republic of Turkey proclaimed.

1924 3 March: Caliphate abolished. 8 April: Religious courts abolished. 26 August: İş-Bank founded. 17 November: Progressive Republican Party formed.

1925 11 February–29 June: First Kurdish insurrection. 5 June: Progressive Republican Party dissolved by the government. 30 September: Religious orders suppressed. 25 November: Wearing of the fez forbidden by law. 26 December: International calendar and international system of time adopted.

1926 17 February: New civil code (based on the Swiss code) adopted, effective 4 October. 1 March: New criminal code (based on the Italian code) adopted, effective 1 July. 5 June: Anglo-Turkish Treaty signed. 28 June: New commercial code (primarily based on the German code) adopted.

1927 7 March: Kurdish revolt under Sheikh Said breaks out; intermittent insurrections brought under virtually complete control in 1938.

1928 10 April: State declared secular. 3 November: Latin alphabet adopted, effective 1 December 1928.

1929 17 June: Suppression of communist propaganda in Turkey.

1930 16 April: Women are given the right to vote in municipal elections. 12 August: Republican Free Party formed. 17 November: Republican Free Party dissolves.

1931 20 April: Republican People’s Party declared republican, nationalist, populist, statist, secular, and revolutionary-reformist.

1932 19 February: People’s Houses opened. 12 August: Turkey joins League of Nations.

1934 9 February: Balkan Pact reached with Greece, Romania, and Yugoslavia. 21 June: Law requiring all citizens to adopt family names adopted, effective 1 January 1935. 26 November: Mustafa Kemal bestowed family name of “Atatürk” (Father of Turks) by National Assembly. 8 December: Women eligible to vote in national elections and become members of the National Assembly.

1935 27 May: Sunday, rather than Friday, becomes the day of rest.

1936 20 July: Montreux Convention signed.

1937 9 July: Sâdabad Pact reached with Iraq, Iran, and Afghanistan.

1938 10 November: Atatürk dies. 11 November: İsmet İnönü becomes president of republic.

1939 29 June: Alexandretta (Hatay) Assembly votes for union with Turkey. 19 October: Ankara Pact signed with Great Britain and France.

1941 18 June: German-Turkish Friendship and Nonaggression Pact signed.

1942 11 November: Wealth tax enacted.

1943 4–6 December: Cairo Conference held; Winston Churchill, Franklin D. Roosevelt, and İsmet İnönü participate.

1945 24 February: Turkey signs United Nations Charter, ratified by National Assembly on 15 August. 7 June: Soviet ultimatum given; Turkey rejects territorial demands.

1946 7 January: Democratic Party founded. 31 May: New electoral law enacted providing for direct and secret ballot.

1947 12 March: President Harry S. Truman announces program of U.S. aid to Greece and Turkey. 12 July: İsmet İnönü’s declaration paves the way for an unhampered opposition and, eventually, multiparty politics.

1948 20 July: Nation Party founded.

1949 24 March: Turkey grants de facto recognition to Israel. 8 August: Turkey admitted to Council of Europe.

1950 16 February: Judiciary given responsibility for the administration of electoral law. 14 May: Democratic Party wins general elections; end of 27-year-old Republican People’s Party rule. 4 July: Israel and Turkey sign trade agreement. 25 July: Turkey sends troops to Korean War.

1952 18 February: Turkey and Greece become full-fledged members in North Atlantic Treaty Organization.

1953 25 February: Nonaggression and Friendship Pact signed with Greece and Yugoslavia.

1954 27 January: Nation Party dissolved by court order on grounds that it seeks to use religion for political purposes. 2 February: Republican Nation Party founded as successor to Nation Party. 2 April: Treaty of Mutual Friendship signed with Pakistan. 9 August: Balkan Pact endorsed with Greece and Yugoslavia.

1955 24 February: Baghdad Pact signed with Iraq, becoming operative 15 April, joined by Great Britain on 4 April, Pakistan on 23 September, and Iran on 11 October. 6 September: Anti-Greek rioting in Istanbul, İzmir, and Ankara. 20 December: Freedom Party established by dissidents in Democratic Party.

1956 6 June: Press Law amended, increasing the government’s powers over the press. 27 June: Law limiting the holding of public political meetings enacted. 26 November: Turkey withdraws its ambassador to Israel until Israel is willing to resolve its differences with the Arabs.

1957 15 January: In U.S.-Turkish agreement, Turkey guaranteed convertibility and transfer of capital and earnings of approved U.S. private investment in Turkey. 6 March: Schools for preachers and prayer leaders given official status.

1958 16 January: Nine army officers arrested for plotting against the government. 24 November: Freedom Party dissolves to merge with Republican People’s Party.

1959 19 February: Greece, Turkey, and Britain agree to establish an independent Cyprus Republic on a communal basis. 5 March: Turkey and United States sign bilateral defense agreement, ratified by Turkey in May 1959. 31 July: Turkey applies for associate membership in European Economic Community.

1960 19 March: Israel and Turkey sign trade and payments agreement. 18 April: All party-political activity suspended for three months, pending an investigation of Republican People’s Party by a National Assembly commission. 28, 30 April–2, 14 May: Student demonstrations held against government. 21 May: Army War College cadets march in Ankara in support of antigovernment demonstrations. 27 May: Officer coup seizes power; General Cemal Gürsel co-opted as its leader. 21 September: Democratic Party (DP) abolished by court order. 14 October: Leaders and parliamentarians of DP go on trial for unconstitutional acts and corruption. 13 November: Gürsel dismisses 14 of the 37 members of National Unity Committee for their radical views.

1961 6 January: Constituent Assembly convenes. 11 February: Justice Party established, also New Turkey Party.

The Second Republic of Turkey

1961 9 July: New constitution ratified in nationwide referendum. 15 September: Celal Bayar (former president), Adnan Menderes (former prime minister), Fatin Rüştü Zorlu (former foreign minister), Hasan Polatkan (former finance minister), and 11 other members of the Democratic Party sentenced to death. Sentences of Bayar and the 11 are commuted to life imprisonment. Other death sentences are executed. 25 October: New, two-house Grand National Assembly convenes.

1962 22 February: Coup attempt led by Colonel Talat Aydemir fails. 26 August: U.S. vice president Lyndon B. Johnson visits Turkey.

1963 21 May: Another coup attempt by Aydemir and fellow officers is put down. 12 September: Turkey becomes an associate member of European Economic Community. 25 December: Turkish warplanes fly over Nicosia as warning against massacre of Turks on Cyprus.

1964 12 March: Turkey warns Archbishop Makarios to stop Greek community’s atrocities toward the Turkish community on the island. 6 June: U.S. president Lyndon B. Johnson dissuades the Turkish government from military intervention in Cyprus.

1965 3 December: Soviet Union contributes to construction of Turkey’s third steel plant.

1966 14 January: U.S. president Lyndon B. Johnson sends terse letter to İsmet İnönü, asking Turks not to launch a military operation in Cyprus. 31 January: İnönü’s firm reply is issued to Johnson, while resentment against U.S. influence in Turkey grows. 8 July: President Cevdet Sunay pardons Celal Bayar, former president of the republic.

1967 30 April: Reliance Party formed.

1968 24 June: Istanbul University closed until 15 July, following student unrest. 25–30 October: French president Charles de Gaulle visits Turkey.

1969 6 January: U.S. ambassador Robert Komer’s car burned by leftist students. 9 February: Alparslan Türkeş elected chairman of newly established Nationalist Action Party. 3 May: Extreme rightists disrupt funeral ceremony of the late president of High Court of Appeals. 31 May: Istanbul University closed, following student siege.

1970 31 January: Pro-Islamic National Order Party formed. 15–16 June: Workers demonstrate in Istanbul and Kocaeli; martial law proclaimed. 22 July: Turkey and European Community sign agreement after Ankara’s completion of the first phase of preparation for future membership. 18 December: Ferruh Bozbeyli and 26 other Justice Party deputies expelled from their party; they form Democratic Party.

1971 20 January: Middle East Technical University closed following student unrest. 3 March: Four American noncommissioned officers are kidnapped and released five days later by urban leftist guerrillas. 12 March: Chief of General Staff and commanders of three forces issue memorandum calling for strong government to fight anarchy and inflation and implement social reforms or face military intervention. Prime Minister Süleyman Demirel resigns. 7 April: Nihat Erim’s above-party government formed at the behest of the military. 27 April: Martial law declared and all student associations banned. 21 May: Constitutional Court closes down National Order Party for antisecular propaganda. 20 July: Constitutional Court closes down Labor Party of Turkey for making communist propaganda and encouraging separatist movements. 20 September: Constitutional amendments adopted by Parliament. 12 October: U.S. vice president Spiro Agnew visits Ankara. 18 October: Queen Elizabeth II visits Turkey.

1972 10 January: Military High Court of Appeals upholds death sentences against three members of Turkish People’s Liberation Army. 8 March: Autonomy of Turkish Radio and TV curtailed. 4 May: General Kemalettin Eken, head of the gendarmerie, wounded by young terrorists. 6 May: Three members of Turkish People’s Liberation Army given death sentences by Military High Court of Appeals executed. 8 May: İsmet İnönü, chairman of Republican People’s Party (RPP), resigns after defeat of his followers at RPP convention. 14 May: Bülent Ecevit becomes chairman of RPP, succeeding İsmet İnönü, who was chairman for 34 years. 4 September: Republican Party formed. 5 December: First Turkish ambassador to Peking (now Beijing) presents his credentials.

1973 3 March: Republican Party unites with Reliance Party to become Republican Reliance Party. 6 April: Senator and retired admiral Fahri Korutürk elected president of the republic. 31 June: Turkey and European Community sign supplementary protocol regulating Turkey’s associate membership. 26 October: Turkey and Soviet Union sign agreement to collaborate on construction of a jointly built dam in Turkey. 25 December: İsmet İnönü dies.

1974 22 April: Law that restores political rights of former Democratic Party members goes into force. 22 June: Socialist Labor Party of Turkey formed. 15 July: Athens-led Cypriot Army takes over government on Cyprus. 20 July: Turkish armed forces intervene to restore peace and stability on Cyprus. 31 July: Turkey, Greece, and Britain sign cease-fire accord on Cyprus. 14 August: Turkish forces in Cyprus hit east and west of Nicosia, the capital, and enter Famagusta as Geneva peace talks fail. 15 October: U.S. president Gerald Ford postpones enactment of a bill to cut military aid to Turkey.

1975 6 February: Turkey suspends talks on the implementation of bilateral accords with United States. 13 February: Turkish Federated State of Cyprus proclaimed. 31 March: Six-month-old government crisis ends as Prime Minister Süleyman Demirel announces “nationalist front” government of Justice Party, Nationalist Action Party, National Salvation Party, and Republican Reliance Party. 26 July: Activities at U.S. military bases in Turkey suspended; Turkish army set to take over full control of bases. 3 October: U.S. House of Representatives votes to partially lift arms embargo on Turkey. 25 December: Soviet premier Aleksey Kosygin visits Ankara.

1976 28 March: Turkey and United States sign new military accord restoring U.S. privileges at defense facilities in Turkey. 12 May: Seventh Islamic Conference opens in Istanbul. 9 August: Ankara sends tough reply to Greece’s note claiming Turkey violated Aegean continental shelf with Seismic I research. 17 September: Tens of thousands of leftist Confederation of Revolutionary Trade Unions member-workers strike to protest government efforts to extend life span of State Security Courts.

1977 3 January: Kirkuk-Iskenderun pipeline inaugurated. 1 May: Thirty-seven dead in May Day rally in Istanbul. 14 August: Turkey claims Greece violated international treaties by militarizing Aegean islands. 30 August: In Great Victory Day message, President Fahri Korutürk says, “Keep army out of politics.” 6 October: Türk-İş (largest labor confederation in Turkey) presents memorandum to government, Parliament, and political parties and demands reforms and threatens general strike.

1978 30 January: Rightist youth stage illegal demonstration in Ankara. 17 March: Turkey strongly criticizes Israeli invasion of Lebanon. 31 May: Prime Minister Ecevit meets U.S. president Jimmy Carter. 10 June: Chief of General Staff General Kenan Evren reacts to wave of violence engulfing Turkey, saying the armed forces will not allow anyone to divide the country. 23 June: Turkey and Soviet Union sign “political document.” 11 July: Gunmen kill Professor Bedrettin Cömert of Hacettepe University in an ambush. 27 September: United States formally lifts embargo on aid to Turkey. 24 December: Sectarian clashes in Kahramanmaraş in southeastern Turkey leave 117 dead and more than 1,000 wounded.

1979 8 March: President Fahri Korutürk once more warns political leaders, “Keep armed forces out of your conflict.” 29 March: U.S. Congress approves $200 million in military aid to Turkey. 12 April: One U.S. serviceman killed and another seriously wounded by gunmen in İzmir. 4 May: U.S. Senate turns down $50 million aid grant proposal to Turkey. 11 May: Gunmen kill one U.S. serviceman and injure another; outlawed Marxist-Leninist Armed Propaganda Union claims responsibility. 22 May: U.S. Senate approves $50 million grant to Turkey. 15 June: Turkish and Greek officials open intercommunal talks on Cyprus. 23 June: Turkey cannot permit U-2 flights over its airspace under present circumstances, says chief of General Staff General Evren. 8 August: Some students at the opening ceremony of Middle East Technical University refuse to stand to attention and force others to sit down when the Turkish national anthem is sung. Instead, they sing the communist “International” and take the oath of revolution. 5 October: Palestinian Liberation Organization (PLO) chief Yasser Arafat inaugurates permanent PLO office in Ankara. 9 October: Government extends (temporary) status of U.S. bases in Turkey. 20 November: Professor Ümit Doğanay, deputy dean of Istanbul University’s political sciences faculty, is assassinated by terrorists.

The Third Republic of Turkey

1980 2 January: Letter of warning by the chief of General Staff and other top army generals calling for urgent action by all “constitutional institutions” and political parties against terrorism is handed over by President Fahri Korutürk to ruling Justice Party leader Süleyman Demirel and opposition Republican People’s Party chairman Bülent Ecevit. 2 February: Confederation of Revolutionary Trade Unions takes general strike decision against government’s economic measures, which it calls “fascist pressure on labor.” 22 February: Turkey unilaterally opens Aegean airspace to air traffic. 28 February: Martial law commander General Nevzat Bölügiray says there is “an undeclared civil war in Turkey.” 18 April: Turkey signs nuclear nonproliferation accord. 8 May: Labor Party of Turkey closed down by the Constitutional Court. 13 May: General Evren urges political parties to elect a new president without delay. 26 May: General Kenan Evren says Turkish armed forces will continue to follow the path drawn by Atatürk. 1 July: Turkey and European Community conclude a new association agreement. 9 July: Police forces reported ineffective in Fatsa township, which is under control of extreme leftist factions and “people’s committees.” 19 July: Former premier Nihat Erim assassinated by four terrorists in Istanbul. 30 August: Angered by National Salvation Party (NSP) chief Necmettin Erbakan’s absence at the Victory Day celebrations, General Evren asks, “Is he against the August 30 victory?” (30 August 1922 was the date of decisive victory over invading Greek forces). 6 September: Group of fanatics refuses to sing national anthem in NSP rally in Konya. 12 September: Turkish armed forces, headed by General Evren, take over the administration. 16 September: Head of state, General Evren, holds his first press conference and says, “Our aim is to protect and safeguard democracy.” 11 October: Ankara military court arrests Nationalist Action Party leader Alparslan Türkeş and 36 party members for “instigating civil war.” 15 October : NSP chairman Erbakan and 21 party members arrested for acting against secular principles of the republic. 27 October: Provisional constitution announced; 1961 constitution to remain in force until a new constitution is drafted. 2 December: Turkey downgrades relations with Israel to minimum. 4 December: Turkey signs $200 million aid agreement with United States.

1981 23 January: Premier Bülend Ulusu attends Islamic summit in Jidda, Saudi Arabia. 14 February: National Security Council (NSC) reminds nation that all political activities have been banned in the country. 15 June: Syria and Turkey sign juridical agreement. 1 October: Political Affairs Committee of Council of Europe recommends continuation of Turkish membership. 16 October: NSC dissolves all political parties. 23 October: Consultative Assembly inaugurated. Head of state Kenan Evren outlines the task of new assembly—to reinstate democracy. 3 November: Martial law court sentences Bülent Ecevit to four months in prison for engaging in political activity.

1982 8 April: Turco-Romanian Economic Cooperation protocol signed. 10 April: Bülent Ecevit in custody for article he wrote in a Norwegian paper. 26 April: Second arrest order for Ecevit for letter he allegedly wrote to a Dutch journalist, later broadcast by BBC. 2 June: Ecevit is acquitted of all charges relating to newspaper article. 23 July: Moratorium announced between Greece and Turkey, which calls on the two countries to refrain from provocative acts and statements. 4 August: NSC lifts restrictions on expression of political views; ban on political comments by former political leaders remains in force.

1982 7 November: National referendum on draft constitution held; 91 percent of those who voted (also 91 percent) approve new constitution; together with the constitutional referendum, General Kenan Evren is elected Turkey’s president. 16 November: Prime Minister Bülend Ulusu meets Soviet prime minister Nikolai Tikhonov in Moscow. 29 November: Turkey and United States to sign a memorandum of understanding for modernization of more than 10 airfields in Turkey. 15 December: People’s Republic of China and Turkey sign accord stipulating increase in economic cooperation.

1983 28 January: Parliamentary Assembly of Council of Europe votes to give “serious consideration” to Turkey’s expulsion from the council because of alleged human rights violations. 24 February: Ankara martial law court sentences Necmettin Erbakan to four years in prison for attempting to establish state based on Islam. 24 April: Ban on political activities lifted. 4 May: Ankara martial law court sentences defunct Workers and Peasants Party of Turkey chairman Doğu Perinçek to 12 years’ imprisonment. 16 May: Nationalist Democracy Party becomes first political party to be set up following 12 September 1980 military takeover. 19 May: Populist Party formed. 20 May: Turgut Özal forms Motherland Party (MP). Grand Turkey Party is established by those close to the defunct Justice Party (JP). 29 May: Professor Erdal İnönü (son of late İsmet İnönü) announces establishment of Social Democracy Party (SDP). 31 May: Military administration closes down Grand Turkey Party, claiming it is a continuation of the defunct JP. 23 June: True Path Party (TPP), filling the vacuum created by the closure of the Grand Turkey Party, is established. Military administration vetoes top brass of Social Democracy Party, including its chairman, Erdal İnönü. 7 July: National Security Council vetoes 30 founders of True Path Party. 24 August: NSC gives approval to participation of Motherland Party in 6 November elections. The council does not approve the list of founding members of SDP and TPP, thus disqualifying them from taking part in the elections. 6 November: MP wins elections by majority. 15 November: Turkish Cypriots announce establishment of Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus (TRNC); Turkey recognizes new state. 29 December: Prime Minister Turgut Özal unveils package of radical economic measures liberalizing imports and taking steps toward full convertibility of Turkish lira.

1984 13 March: President Li Xiannian arrives in Ankara to become first Chinese head of state to visit Turkey. 2 May: Turkey and West Germany sign cooperation agreement for peaceful use of nuclear energy. 13 November: Permanent Economic Committee of the Organization of Islamic Conference opens three days of meetings with an inaugural speech by President Kenan Evren, the committee’s chairman. 25 December: Soviet premier Nikolai Tikhonov arrives in Ankara for official visit.

1985 13 February: Martial law tribunal acquits leaders of defunct National Salvation Party of charges of attempting to set up state based on Islam. 2 April: Prime Minister Turgut Özal meets U.S. president Ronald Reagan. 9 July: Helmut Kohl, chancellor of Federal Republic of Germany, arrives in Turkey for official visit. 3 November: Populist Party and Social Democracy Party merge to form Social Democratic Populist Party. 14 November: Democratic Left Party founded by Rahşan Ecevit (wife of Bülent Ecevit).

1986 4 May: Opposition Nationalist Democracy Party (NDP) extraordinary convention dissolves the party. 9 May: Former Turkish Union of Chambers president Mehmet Yazar establishes Free Democratic Party, along with 22 former NDP deputies. 16 May: True Path Party forms parliamentary group after 20 former independent deputies join the party. 18 May: Former prime minister Bülent Ecevit returns to political scene. 30 May: Erdal İnönü elected new chairman of Social Democratic Populist Party (SDPP). 15 August: Turkish warplanes bomb separatist rebel hideouts in northern Iraq four days after 12 Turkish soldiers are killed near the border. 24 October: Prime Minister Turgut Özal breaks ground for 847-kilometer pipeline that will bring Soviet natural gas to Turkey. 30 November: Free Democratic Party dissolves after by-election defeat. 19 December: Greek and Turkish soldiers clash at border. 26 December: People’s Party established by 20 former SDPP deputies. 29 December: People’s Party dissolves itself; 19 of its deputies join Democratic Left Party.

1987 8 January: President Kenan Evren in speech says Muslim fundamentalism has been resurrected in Turkey and calls on state officials and people to struggle against all kinds of extremism. 10 January: Former prime minister Bülent Ecevit sentenced to prison term of 11 months for speech made during September 1986 election campaign in which he allegedly violated a political ban against former political leaders. 25 January: President Evren flies to Kuwait to attend two-day summit of heads of Islamic countries. 26 January: Turkey recognizes individual rights of Turkish citizens to apply to European Human Rights Commission. 4 March: Turkish jet fighters bomb separatist rebel camps and ammunition depots in northern Iraq in retaliation for separatist killings of civilians in Turkey. 16 March: Turkey and United States extend 1980 Turkish-American Defense and Economic Cooperation Agreement until 18 December 1990. 26 March: Turkey counters Greek decision to explore for oil in disputed areas of Aegean Sea. 27 March: Turkish armed forces are placed in state of readiness as tensions mount between Greece and Turkey. 28 March: Turkey receives assurances from Greece that it will not explore for oil in disputed waters of Aegean Sea. 7 April: Former Nationalist Action Party chairman Alparslan Türkeş sentenced to prison term of 11 years; party leadership accused of plotting ultranationalist armed revolt in the country. 14 April: Turkey applies to European Community for full membership. 29 June: Prime Minister Turgut Özal announces that General Necip Torumtay will become Turkey’s chief of General Staff rather than General Necdet Öztorun, widely believed to be the army’s choice. 14 July: Government establishes office of emergency rule regional governor to coordinate fight against terrorism in eight eastern and southeastern provinces. 6 September: National referendum lifts bans against political leaders who ruled the country before the 1980 military intervention, with a razor-thin majority. 13 September: Bülent Ecevit becomes chairman of Democratic Left Party. 24 September: Süleyman Demirel becomes chairman of True Path Party. 4 October: Alparslan Türkeş becomes chairman of Nationalist Work Party. 11 October: Necmettin Erbakan becomes chairman of Welfare Party. 29 November: General elections held; Motherland Party retains majority of seats in Parliament.

1988 11 January: Turkey signs Council of Europe’s Convention on Prevention of Torture and Inhuman or Degrading Treatment or Punishment. 25 January: Turkey signs United Nations’ international convention against inhuman treatment and torture. 1 February: Socialist Party founded. 6 April: British prime minister Margaret Thatcher arrives for three-day official visit. 26 June: President Kenan Evren begins five-day visit to United States. 12 July: President Evren starts three-day visit to Great Britain. 11 October: Government liberalizes bank interest rates. 16 October: President Evren flies to Federal Republic of Germany for five-day official visit; he tells journalists that articles of Penal Code dealing with communism should be scrapped to open the way for the establishment of a Communist Party in Turkey. 3 December: Council of Higher Education, the highest body of Turkish universities, lifts ban against Islamic-style head scarves for female university students. 8 December: Constitutional Court rejects request by chief prosecutor to close down Socialist Party. 16 December: Prime Minister Turgut Özal meets with U.S. president Ronald Reagan and President-Elect George H. W. Bush at White House.

1989 2 February: Turkey and Iran sign agreement in Ankara, reviving a 52-year-old border security pact that aims to curb drug smuggling and rebel activity. 7 March: Constitutional Court annuls law allowing female students to wear Islamic-style head scarves at universities. 11 April: Labor unrest spreads throughout Turkey after government and trade union negotiators fail to agree on pay hike for 600,000 workers employed by the state. 13 April: Konya municipality lifts its decision to segregate male and female students on buses after wide-scale student protests. 16 May: Turkey grants United States permission to modernize Pirinçlik listening station near the southeastern city of Diyarbakır. 17 August: In an unprecedented move, the armed forces issue statement declaring they “will do everything to combat separatist terrorism that aims at destroying the national existence and territorial integrity of the country,” following a sudden escalation in separatist incidents in southeastern Turkey. 17 September: Central Bank announces it has completed payment of country’s rescheduled foreign debts, introduced 22 years earlier under the name of “Convertible Turkish Lira Accounts.” 31 October: Parliament elects Prime Minister Turgut Özal as president. 17 November: Yıldırım Akbulut elected chairman of Motherland Party. 29 November: Turkey approves European Social Charter. 8 December: After 60 years of illegality, the clandestine Turkish United Communist Party announces its decision to end its “illegal” status and establish a legal Communist Party in Turkey.

1990 31 January: Professor Muammer Aksoy assassinated; two separate unknown Islamic fundamentalist groups claim responsibility for killing the ardently secularist professor. 4 February: European Community foreign ministers agree to delay negotiations with Turkey on its full membership request; however, all members, with the exception of Greece, say they wish closer relations with Turkey. 5 April: International Monetary Fund designates Turkish lira fully convertible currency. 1 May: May Day turns sour as left-wing supporters try to stage mass rallies in Istanbul and clash with police; 1,100 taken into custody. 17 May: Democratic Center Party of Bedrettin Dalan established. 4 June: Turkish United Communist Party founded. 7 June: Independent deputies who quit the main opposition Social Democratic Populist Party establish People’s Toiling Party. 2 August: Turkey voices deep concern as Iraq invades Kuwait and asks Baghdad to restore Kuwaiti territorial integrity and sovereignty. 8 August: Turkey joins United Nations Security Council sanctions against Iraq and closes down the twin pipeline carrying Iraqi crude oil exports to its Mediterranean terminal at Yumurtalık. 12 August: Parliament gives government permission to send troops abroad and allows foreign forces to be stationed on Turkish soil only if Turkey is attacked. 5 September: Parliament gives authority to the government to send Turkish troops abroad and allow foreign troops to be stationed in Turkey without restrictions. 18 September: Defense and Economic Cooperation Agreement between Turkey and United States extended for another year. 23 September: President Turgut Özal goes to United States to meet President George H. W. Bush. 6 October: Professor Bahriye Üçok, known for her strong prosecular views, is killed in a parcel bomb attack. 19 November: President Özal and Prime Minister Yıldırım Akbulut sign historic treaty that cuts conventional forces in Europe and ends Cold War. 3 December: Chief of General Staff General Necip Torumtay resigns, saying the principles he believes in and his understanding of government render it impossible for him to continue in office. 5 December: Parliament votes to establish Parliamentary Human Rights Commission. 19 December: Government asks North Atlantic Treaty Organization to deploy Allied mobile forces in southeastern Turkey against possible Iraqi attack.

1991 17 January: Parliament gives added war powers to the government, including permission for the United States to use Turkish air bases. 12 March: Turkey and the Soviet Union sign Friendship and Cooperation Treaty. 23 March: At joint White House press conference with U.S. president George H. W. Bush, President Turgut Özal says Turkey will not allow the creation of a Kurdish state in northern Iraq. 12 April: Bill lifts ban on speaking in Kurdish. 13 May: Unidentified terrorists fatally shoot retired lieutenant general İsmail Selen in Ankara and gendarmerie commander Brigadier General Temel Cingöz in Adana. 5 June: President Özal says it is unthinkable that Turkey will shoulder its share of the military burden of European security while being left out of other areas in the “new Europe.” 6 July: Turkey’s first female governor appointed to Muğla province. 20 July: President Bush arrives in Turkey for two-day visit. 29 July: Turkey forbids allied forces to launch future punitive air strikes against Iraq from Turkish air bases. 15 August: In İzmir, police arrest at least 44 Kurdish rebels participating in celebrations of the seventh anniversary of the Kurdish separatist struggle in Turkey. 19 August: British businessman Andrew Blake killed in Istanbul; left-wing and Islamic groups both claim responsibility for the assassination. 14 September: Democratic Center Party merges with True Path Party. 17 September: In Ankara, Patriotic Union of Kurdistan leader Talabani asks President Özal to lobby for continued presence of allied force in Turkey to protect Kurds in Iraq from possible attacks by that government. 1 October: Saudi king Fahd informs President Özal that his country will donate $1 billion to the Turkish Defense Fund by providing Turkey with $200 million in crude oil each year for five years. 21 October: Prime Minister Mesut Yılmaz resigns, as his Motherland Party trails behind the True Path Party (TPP) at the 20 October general elections. 24–26 October: Turkish jets raid Kurdish rebel camps in northern Iraq. 19 November: TPP leader Süleyman Demirel signs pact with Social Democratic Populist Party leader Erdal İnönü to form a coalition government; the coalition controls 266 of 450 seats. 25 December: In Istanbul, firebombs are thrown at department store owned by the brother of Necati Çetinkaya, the recently appointed governor-general of Turkey’s southeastern provinces. 26 December: In Paris, a previously unknown group called the Kurdistan Committee seizes the Turkish embassy to protest the alleged assassination of 30 people in Kulp and Lice (both in southeastern Turkey) by the Turkish army. 29 December: Nationalist Action Party (NAP) merges with Nationalist Labor Party (NLP). The NLP then elects former NAP leader Alparslan Türkeş as its leader.

1992 15 January: Parliamentary Human Rights Commission presents a report proposing stringent security measures combined with religious propaganda to combat the spread of Kurdish nationalism. 19 January: Speaker of Parliament rejects request by Ankara State Security Court to lift the parliamentary immunity of 22 former members of Kurdish-backed People’s Toiling Party, who entered Parliament on the Social Democratic Populist Party (SDPP) ticket. 2 February: Prime Minister Süleyman Demirel and Greek prime minister Constantine Mitsotakis agree to prepare accord of “friendship, good-neighborliness, and cooperation” and back UN-sponsored efforts to reunite Cyprus. 3 February: Black Sea Economic Cooperation Project initialed by foreign ministers of nine countries in Istanbul. 11 February: In talks in Washington, D.C., U.S. president George H. W. Bush and Prime Minister Demirel agree to increase aid to Central Asian and Transcaucasia republics. 16 February: Government increases customs duties and/or special fund provisions on more than 70 key import commodities, while denying return to protectionism. 21 February: Turkey conducts military exercises near Armenian border against background of growing tension between Azerbaijan and Armenia over the disputed enclave of Nagorno-Karabakh. 26 February: Parliamentary Human Rights Commission concludes that ban on head scarves in universities is an infringement of human rights. 3 March: Prime Minister Demirel calls on United States and Russian Federation not to arm Armenia amid growing fears that conflict over Nagorno-Karabakh could drag into neighboring countries. 9 March: Prime Minister Demirel announces that Kurds can celebrate Newroz (Kurdish New Year) on 21 March. 13 March: European Parliament condemns Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) but calls for a halt to cross-border operations because civilians are being killed. 18 March: Prime Minister Demirel asks United States to seek diplomatic solution to fighting between Armenians and Azerbaijanis over Nagorno-Karabakh and says Turkey is being forced to get involved. 21–22 March: Clashes erupt between army and Kurds following Kurdish rebels’ call on supporters to stage demonstrations during the Newroz. 26 March: Ankara and Washington sign agreement enabling Turkey to produce 40 additional F-16 fighter planes. Germany announces plans to suspend all arms shipments to Turkey until Ankara guarantees that the weapons are not being used against population in southeast. 30 March: Prime Minister Demirel warns Syria to stop supporting PKK rebels. 26 April: Prime Minister Demirel begins trip to Azerbaijan, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, and Uzbekistan in effort to further develop Turkey’s relations with newly established Central Asian countries. 5 May: Germany lifts ban on military aid to Turkey. 7 June: Local by-elections held: True Path Party wins 173 municipalities; Social Democratic Populist Party, 70; Motherland Party, 52; Welfare Party, 15; Democratic Left Party, 1. 13 June: Tansu Çiller becomes True Path Party (TPP) leader. 2 July: Ban lifted on political parties closed down by 1980 military intervention. 5 July: Tansu Çiller becomes prime minister, to lead TPP-SDPP coalition. 10 July: Constitutional Court bans Socialist Party on charges of engaging in separatist activity. 14 July: Constitutional Court closes pro-Kurdish People’s Toiling Party. 27 August: Turkey establishes diplomatic relations with Bosnia-Herzegovina, Croatia, Macedonia, and Slovenia. 9 September: Republican People’s Party, banned after 1980 military intervention, reopens; Deniz Baykal elected chairman. 10 September: Democratic Party, closed by military after 1960 coup, reopens after 32 years; former foreign minister Hayrettin Erkmen becomes chairman. 14 September: Iran agrees to cooperate with Turkey in efforts to fight PKK. 19 September: Party members raise Kurdish flag and sing their national anthem during second People’s Toiling Party extraordinary convention in Ankara. 7 October: New Party established. 14 October: Financial Times survey ranks Turkey among the top 30 countries in the world in terms of creditworthiness and ability to pay. 6 November: Socialist Turkey Party founded. 15 November: Turkey and Israel sign a treaty of friendship. 19 November: Criminal Trials Procedure Act amended in more liberal direction. 23 November: Hasan Celal Güzel founds Resurrection Party and becomes its chairman. 19 December: Justice Party convention closes the party and hands over all property and original emblem to TPP. 24 December: Parliament renews mandate for Operation Provide Comfort for protecting the northern Iraqis.

1993 14 January: Turkish armed forces put on red alert following allied air strikes on Iraq. Prime Minister Süleyman Demirel visits Syria, where he is told that Syria will not back Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) rebels. 23 January: A secret report submitted to the National Security Council (NSC) accuses Hizbullah (Party of God) of committing unsolved murders in the southeast and seeking to introduce Sharia law in the country. 29 January: Great Unity Party established. 30 January: All European Union (EU) countries, except Denmark, Great Britain, and Ireland, are to issue “joint visas” to Turkish citizens. 9 February: Prime Minister Demirel reveals that the Islamic Action group that claimed responsibility in the murder of journalist Uğur Mumcu had been trained in Iran. 23 February: NSC proposes an economic package for the southeast since “recent military operations have broken the back of the PKK.” 3 March: Turkey and EU are to establish a commission to oversee transition to Customs Union due in 1995. 15 March: Government refuses to negotiate with PKK because it is a “terrorist organization.” 17 March: PKK leader Abdullah Öcalan unilaterally declares a 25-day cease-fire; PKK fighters will not disarm until peace accord is reached with government. 16 April: At press conference in Bar İlyas, Lebanon, Abdullah Öcalan announces indefinite extension of cease-fire begun on March 20. 17 April: President Turgut Özal dies of heart attack. 16 May: Parliament elects Süleyman Demirel president of the republic. Erdal İnönü becomes caretaker prime minister. 12 June: U.S. secretary of state Warren Christopher asks Turkish government for compliance with U.S. proposal to reduce human rights violations. 13 June: True Path Party elects Tansu Çiller as party leader. 14 June: President Demirel appoints Çiller prime minister. 2 July: Islamic rioters set fire to a hotel in Sivas that accommodated leftist writers and intellectuals, whom they accuse of spreading atheism. Forty people die while Aziz Nesin, who had published Salman Rushdie’s Satanic Verses and who apparently was the primary target, survives. 15 July: Constitutional Court bans Kurdish-backed People’s Toiling Party. 16 August: Foreign Minister Hikmet Çetin urges U.S. secretary of state Warren Christopher to help lift UN oil sanctions against Iraq, pointing out that sanctions not only hurt Iraqi government but also Iraqi and Turkish peoples. 11 September: Ankara mayor Murat Karayalçın elected Republican People’s Party leader. 14 October: Prime Minister Çiller arrives in United States for meetings with U.S. president Bill Clinton and other U.S. officials. 22 October: Rebels kill Brigadier General Bahtiyar Aydın in Lice. 29 November: Prime Ministry announces that air strikes were carried out against nine separatist targets in northern Iraq, with the knowledge of Iraqi authorities. 12 December: Hatip Dicle becomes pro-Kurdish Democracy Party leader. 23 December: Four pro-Kurdish Democracy Party deputies’ parliamentary immunity is lifted, making them liable for prosecution by Ankara State Security Court.

1994 28 February: Prime Minister Tansu Çiller calls for a public rally at Istanbul’s Taksim Square to defend secularism against fundamentalist attacks symbolically aimed at Atatürk’s memory. 21 March: Government adopts a flexible attitude toward celebration of Newroz (Kurdish New Year). 27 March: At local elections, the municipalities of Ankara and Istanbul go to Welfare Party. 14 April: Washington announces that the International Monetary Fund will support the government’s stabilization program. 15 April: First meeting of Welfare Party–controlled Istanbul Municipality’s Council starts with Welfarists praying, while secular members sing the national anthem. 4 May: World Bank approves a $100 million credit to support government’s privatization plans. 12 May: People’s Democracy Party founded by members of Democracy Party. Government authorizes preliminary work on first nuclear power plant in Akkuyu. 18 May: Government announces “democratization package.” 7 June: Turkey warns Greece that any attempt to extend its territorial waters to 12 miles will be tantamount to a declaration of war. 16 June: Twelve leading deputies of Democracy Party resign from their party. 17 June: Constitutional Court bans Democracy Party. 1 July: Turkey unilaterally imposes new shipping regulations for the straits of Bosporus and Dardanelles, including requiring Turkish permission for the passage of ships more than 150 meters long. 26 July: Liberal Party formed by Besim Tibuk. 10 August: Turkey’s second communications satellite, Türksat 1B, on course. 27 August: Government rejects a plan for U.S. military aid, requiring favorable report on human rights in Turkey and on Greek-Turkish negotiations over Cyprus before the release of aid. 1 September: European Union raises its quotas for imports of Turkish textiles by an average of 35 percent. 9 September: Turkey and Greece agree to start up regular talks as a means of solving their differences. 16 October: Doğu Perinçek reelected Labor Party leader. 19 October: President Süleyman Demirel refutes Russian Federation charges that Turkey is trying to create an ethnically based sphere of influence within the Commonwealth of Independent States. 3 November: Turkey and Israel sign agreements on joint struggle against drug trafficking, terrorism, and other crimes and on communications and postal services. 6 November: Social Democratic Populist Party and new Republican People’s Party merge. 9 November: President Demirel launches Southeast Anatolia Project—a hydroelectric and irrigation project consisting of a complex of 22 dams on the Euphrates and Tigris Rivers; as it could reduce water supplies to Iraq and Syria, both countries oppose the plan. 8 December: Five Kurdish members of Parliament—Selim Andak, Hatip Dicle, Orhan Doğan, Ahmet Türk, and Leyla Zana—are convicted of supporting the Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) and sentenced to 15 years in prison. 21 December: High Military Court dismisses six officers from army because of their fundamentalist Islamic activities within ranks. 22 December: Rich textile heir Cem Boyner’s New Democracy Movement transformed into a political party.

1995 10 January: Prime Minister Tansu Çiller announces that Newroz (Kurdish New Year) is an official holiday in Turkey. 15 January: Greece agrees to withdraw its veto against Turkey’s entry to Customs Union. 19 February: Republican People’s Party (RPP) and Social Democratic People’s Party merge under RPP roof; Hikmet Çetin becomes leader of new party. 6 March: Turkey’s entry into Customs Union with European Union approved. 12 March: After an unidentified group opens automatic gunfire on a neighborhood coffeehouse, riots by Alevite community break out in poor districts of Istanbul, leading to clashes with police; life and property lost; army units step in and curfew imposed. 18 March: Germany bans all Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) activities within its borders and starts to deport illegal activists back to Turkey. 20 March: Government forces numbering 35,000 enter northern Iraq to conduct operations against PKK rebels with armored battalions. 2 April: U.S. deputy secretary of state Richard Holbrooke supports Turkey’s operation in northern Iraq, adding that security of Turkey’s borders affects the security of Europe. 11 April: PKK leader Abdullah Öcalan says he is prepared to negotiate a political solution to the conflict in the southeast; government not willing to negotiate with a “terrorist.” 19 April: Prime Minister Çiller meets with U.S. president Bill Clinton in Washington, D.C.; Clinton urges Çiller to pull Turkish forces out of northern Iraq. 21 April: Armenia and Turkey agree to reopen an air route between Erzurum in eastern Turkey and Yerevan in Armenia. 26 April: Netherlands refuses to ban Kurdish Parliament in exile at The Hague; in return, Turkish government bars the Netherlands from bidding on defense contracts. 27 April: United States and Japan devise a $500 million loan for Turkey. 30 April: President Süleyman Demirel refuses to go to Moscow to attend celebrations marking 50th anniversary of the end of World War II in protest of Russian Federation aggressions against Chechens in that federation. 8 May: Nationalist Action Party leader Alparslan Türkeş says Turks and Kurds lived together for 900 years and, consequently, he cannot imagine a Turk being an enemy of a Kurd. 13 May: Russian Federation promises to exclude PKK activities from Russian Federation. 1 June: Despite Turkish protests, Greece extends its territorial waters to 12 miles. 9 July: Accord reached with Uzbekistan for the transport of Uzbek natural gas to Turkey via Turkmenistan–Georgia line. 23 July: Parliament lowers voting age from 21 to 18 and allows political participation by unions. International Securities Free Zone established in Istanbul. 28 July: Istanbul Gold Exchange inaugurated. 10 August: Accord reached between Turkey and Bosnia-Herzegovina; Turkey will train Bosnian troops and aid the Bosnian defense industry. 10 September: Deniz Baykal becomes Republican People’s Party (RPP) leader. 20 September: Prime Minister Çiller resigns following withdrawal of RPP from its coalition with Çiller’s True Path Party (TPP). 5 November: Çiller’s TPP and Baykal’s RPP form coalition government. 2 December: Religiously oriented Welfare Party (WP) declares it is not against bank interest. 13 December: European Parliament admits Turkey into Customs Union with European Union, effective 1 January 1996. 14 December: PKK leader Abdullah Öcalan declares a unilateral cease-fire. 24 December: General elections held. Religiously oriented WP obtains plurality of votes, followed by True Path Party, Motherland Party, Democratic Left Party, and Republican People’s Party.

1996 27 January: Political crisis erupts over Kardak islets on the Aegean Sea amid Turkish and Greek claims of sovereignty over islets. 13 February: Turkmenistan and Turkey sign accord for supply of natural gas to Turkey. 13 March: Motherland Party (MP) and True Path Party (TPP) form coalition government; Mesut Yılmaz of the MP will become prime minister for one year, Tansu Çiller of the TPP will take over prime ministry from Yılmaz for two years, and an unnamed member of the MP will serve as prime minister during the last two years of the parliamentary term. 21 March: Prime Minister Mesut Yılmaz celebrates Newroz (Kurdish New Year) in the southeastern town of Iğdır. 24 March: Parliament votes to conduct an investigation into charges that former prime minister Tansu Çiller manipulated government contracts for personal gain. 8 April: Arab League pronounces signing of military cooperation agreement between Turkey and Israel as “show of ill will” and an “act of aggression.” 10 April: Tension between Iran and Turkey mounts over countercharges of spying. 23 April: Parliament approves Welfare Party motion to open investigation on former prime minister Çiller for her part in mishandling of privatization bid; Athens vetoes 3.4 billion euros earmarked for Turkey by the European Union (EU). 25 May: TPP leader Çiller withdraws her party from coalition. 26 May: Council of Ministers meets in southeastern city of Diyarbakır, underlining the importance of the region. 2 June: Local elections held; Welfare Party (WP) garners plurality of votes, followed by Motherland Party (MP), True Path Party (TPP), Democratic Left Party, Grand Turkey Party, Republican People’s Party, Nationalist Action Party, and People’s Democracy Party. 6 June: Prime Minister Yılmaz resigns, ending the TPP-MP coalition. WP leader Necmettin Erbakan assures that his party is not antidemocratic, it has no plans to relinquish Turkey’s membership in the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, and it backs a customs union with the EU. Government rejects $22 million economic aid package from United States because of stipulations calling for Turkey to cease its blockade of a humanitarian aid package to Armenia. 12 June: President Süleyman Demirel responds harshly to claims by Saudi Arabia that Turkey’s cooperation pact with Israel could deteriorate relations with Arab world. 13 June: Government armed forces launch a new offensive into northern Iraq; 5,000 troops go seven kilometers into territory. 19 June: Croatia and Turkey sign agreement on military cooperation. WP votes with TPP to turn down a former WP motion to hold parliamentary investigations into charges that TPP leader Çiller misused discretionary funds at her disposal as then prime minister. 23 June: In Ankara, 30 leading members of pro-Kurdish People’s Democracy Party arrested after a party convention where the Turkish flag was brought down by masked militants. 28 June: WP and TPP form coalition government. WP leader Necmettin Erbakan is prime minister and TPP leader Çiller deputy prime minister and foreign minister. 11 July: Turkish warplanes hit Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) base on Iraqi border. 19 October: Deputy Prime Minister Çiller announces new democratization and human rights package in response to criticism from Europe. 25 November: Prime Minister Erbakan announces he will not attend EU conference in Dublin. Parliamentary committee investigating charges of corruption against former prime minister Çiller declares charges unsubstantiated. 28 November: Parliamentary commission studying corruption charges against deputy prime minister and foreign minister Çiller decides against sending her to High Court.

1997 20 January: Turkey and Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus (TRNC) sign historic declaration: Any attack on the TRNC is tantamount to an attack on Turkey itself. 23 January: Prime Minister Necmettin Erbakan heavily criticized for inviting leaders of religious orders to dinner at his official residence. 28 February: National Security Council states that “secularism is not only a form of government but also a way of life and the guarantee of democracy and social peace,” a warning to the Erbakan government to refrain from efforts to Islamize society and polity; the council recommends to the government 20 specific measures to combat “reactionary Islam.” 15 April: Turkey becomes a full member of Western European Union. 28 April: Black Sea Economic Cooperation Conference held in Istanbul. 30 April: Greece and Turkey agree to establish a group of “wise men” to help resolve their differences. 5 May: Israel, Turkey, and United States to conduct joint naval exercises in the Mediterranean at the end of summer; strong reactions come from Arab countries. 28 May: Major unions and business representatives agree to hold a huge protest rally against the Erbakan government. 30 May: U.S. president Bill Clinton opens the way for Turkey to receive $22 million from the Economic Support Fund in 1997. 12 June: Office of chief of General Staff announces it has set up a West Study Group to better monitor Islamic fundamentalism in the country. 18 June: Prime Minister Erbakan resigns and calls on President Süleyman Demirel to appoint Tansu Çiller prime minister. 30 June: Democratic Left Party of Bülent Ecevit, Democratic Turkey Party of Hüsamettin Cindoruk, and Motherland Party of Mesut Yılmaz form coalition government; Yılmaz is prime minister. 6 July: Nationalist Action Party elects Devlet Bahçeli as new leader. 8 July: Greek prime minister Costas Simitis and President Demirel pledge to reconcile differences without use of force and recognize each country’s legitimate interests in Aegean Sea. 16 August: Parliament adopts eight-year compulsory secular education. 30 September: Prime Minister Yılmaz obtains German chancellor Helmut Kohl’s support for Turkey’s European Union (EU) candidacy. 10 November: In a change of policy encouraged by French president Jacques Chirac and German chancellor Helmut Kohl, EU foreign ministers agree in principle to invite Turkey to the EU conference. 4 December: Government issues a set of directives intended to curb police brutality of suspects, including surprise visits to police stations. 13 December: EU excludes Turkey in membership talks for the first and second wave of union expansion; Ankara resolves to suspend relations with EU. 19 December: Prime Minister Yılmaz threatens to withdraw Turkey’s application to join the EU if the union does not reverse its decision to exclude Turkey from the next wave of expansion.

1998 16 January: Constitutional Court bans Welfare Party “because of evidence confirming its actions against the principles of the secular republic.” 8 February: Fifty thousand Turkish soldiers enter a 240-kilometer-long “buffer zone” in northern Iraq to prevent an influx of Kurdish refugees to Turkey in the event of war. 7 March: Prime Minister Mesut Yılmaz accuses Germany of following a policy of lebensraum (creating a living space for Germany) to block Turkey’s membership in the European Union. 17 March: Appeals court acquits former prime minister Tansu Çiller on one of a series of charges made against her on the grounds that there was no evidence Çiller knowingly misused government funds. 27 March: National Security Council recommends to Yılmaz government a list of steps to “curb the influence of those who wish to condemn the Turkish people to a backward way of life.” 16 April: Parliament votes to open new investigation into former prime minister Çiller’s accumulation of wealth between 1991 and 1996. 22 April: Parliament votes to investigate personal finances of Prime Minister Yılmaz. 29 April: Court orders former prime minister Necmettin Erbakan to stand trial for defying the judiciary. 10 May: Reformist group in Virtue Party (VP), led by Bülent Arınç, Recep Tayyip Erdoğan, and Abdullah Gül, wishes to democratize the party and pull it closer to the center of political spectrum. 12 May: Parliament votes to open new investigations against Prime Minister Yılmaz over allegations that he improperly awarded a contract to supporters to build an airport in Istanbul. 15 May: VP, successor party to Welfare Party, elects Recai Kutan as its leader. 20 May: Chief of General Staff Hakkı Karadayı officially warns Russian Federation government regarding their plans to sell S-300 missiles to the Republic of Cyprus. 7 July: Turkey protests Greek militarization of islands in Aegean Sea, near Turkey’s coast. 7 September: Israeli and Turkish prime ministers meet in Israel to discuss ways to develop trade between the two countries. VP parliamentarian Ersönmez Yarbay states that the new VP would have a less dogmatic and more contemporary image than its predecessor, the WP. 6 October: Government announces a 10-day ultimatum: if Syria does not curb its support of the Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK), the military will start cross-border operations to PKK targets in Syria. 6 November: Turkey imposes new navigation rules for Bosporus Strait, including the ability to stop traffic when currents are unfavorable, stop any ship on legal grounds, and require more ships to use local pilots. 8 November: Military pursues PKK rebels into northern Iraq. 19 November: Authorities arrest People’s Democracy Party chairperson Murat Bozlak for referring to Abdullah Öcalan in public as a “party leader” rather than a “terrorist.” 23 November: True Path Party and Motherland Party cooperate to save their leaders, Çiller and Yılmaz, respectively. In the voting, the parliamentary commission investigating their cases decides against sending the leaders to High Court. 25 November: Prime Minister Yılmaz’s government loses a vote of confidence due to corruption allegations.

1999 17 January: Minority government formed by Democratic Left Party leader Bülent Ecevit receives vote of confidence; government is supported from outside by Motherland Party and True Path Party. 16 February: Greek embassy in Nairobi, Kenya, hands over Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) leader Abdullah Öcalan to Kenyan authorities; while on his way to an unspecified destination in Nairobi, Öcalan is captured by Turkish commando units and flown to Turkey on a Turkish plane sent for this operation to Kenya. 15 March: Fifteen thousand members of Turkish government forces enter Iraq in hot pursuit of PKK rebels. 18 April: General elections held; Democratic Left Party of Ecevit obtains plurality of votes, followed by Motherland Party (MP) of Mesut Yılmaz, Nationalist Action Party (NAP) of Devlet Bahçeli, and True Path Party (TPP) of Tansu Çiller. Virtue Party (VP) of Recai Kutan, Republican People’s Party, and People’s Toiling Party votes remain below 10 percent threshold. 30 April: U.S. State Department report criticizes Germany, Italy, and Greece for their lack of conviction in Turkey’s fight against one of the world’s major terror and drug-smuggling organizations, namely PKK. 2 May: President Süleyman Demirel says head scarf is a symbol of political Islam; VP’s newly elected deputy, Merve Kavakçı, is prevented from taking oath of office when she refuses to remove her head scarf. Prime Minister Ecevit emphatically declares, “Parliament is not a place to defy the state.” 28 May: Coalition government among Democratic Left Party (DLP), Nationalist Action Party, and Motherland Party formed. DLP leader Bülent Ecevit is prime minister. 18 June: Military judges removed from state security courts. 26 June: Prime Minister Ecevit releases a circular on human rights and freedom of thought, asking that directives issued to date be strictly adhered to. Republican People’s Party chooses Altan Öymen as new leader. 29 June: Court sentences PKK leader Öcalan to death for treason. 26 September: Turkey to be included in newly formed G20 countries, which comprise G7 countries, 10 large developing countries, and representatives from the European Union (EU), International Monetary Fund (IMF), and World Bank. 28 September: Prime Minister Ecevit meets U.S. president Bill Clinton at White House. Clinton expresses U.S. interest in finding a solution to lingering Cyprus crisis, says improvements in human rights and Greek-Turkey relations will reflect in the process of Turkey’s full membership in the EU, and gives assurances that a Kurdish state will not be established in northern Iraq. 3 November: During state visit in Moscow, Prime Minister Ecevit says Turkey respects territorial integrity of Russian Federation; however, he adds, Turkey is concerned about civilian casualties in Chechnya. 14 November: President Clinton comes to Turkey to attend the Organization of Security and Co-operation in Europe (OSCE) summit in Istanbul. 15 November: In a speech made at the Turkish National Assembly, President Clinton says Turkey plays a critical role in the development of the region and that in the 21st century it should take courageous steps so that it continues to have such an impact. 17 November: Black Sea Economic Cooperation summit convenes in Istanbul. In his opening speech, President Demirel says that the Black Sea Economic Community will serve to link Asia and Europe, on the one hand, and the Black Sea, the Caspian Sea, and Mediterranean basins on the other hand to promote peace and prosperity in the region. 18 November: OSCE summit opens in Istanbul. In his opening speech, President Demirel says everyone failed to adopt timely measures to stem recent conflicts arising from ethnic problems. Azerbaijani president Ilham Aliyev, Georgian president Eduard Shevardnadze, and President Demirel sign package agreements on Baku–Tbilisi–Ceyhan cross-border pipeline. 10 December: At Helsinki Summit, Turkey named candidate country for EU. 22 December: Turkey and IMF sign standby agreement; government promises to launch series of economic reforms over next three years in exchange for IMF loans totaling $4 billion. 27 December: President Demirel wishes Christian citizens of Turkey a Merry Christmas, the first official state recognition of the holiday.

2000 3 February: In the first visit to Greece by a Turkish foreign minister, İsmail Cem arrives in Athens to sign five accords ranging from culture to maritime transit. 9 February: PKK announces it has ended its armed struggle against the government forces and that it will pursue its efforts “within the framework of peace and democracy.” 10 February: VP breaks a taboo of its own and celebrates Valentine’s Day. 4 March: Court of Appeals allows use of Kurdish names. 10 March: Former prime minister Necmettin Erbakan is given one-year prison sentence on the grounds that a speech he made in 1994 incited hatred and enmity among people. 5 May: Parliament elects Ahmet Necdet Sezer, former chairman of the Constitutional Court, as Turkey’s 10th president. 14 May: VP leader Recai Kutan reelected party’s chairman. 17 July: European Union (EU) asks Turkey to allow for broadcasting and education in Kurdish as conditions for inclusion in the EU as a full member. 21 July: Turkish Petroleum Agency privatized. 15 August: Turkey signs United Nations Civil and Political Rights Charter and the Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights Charter. 30 August: Public prosecutor files a suit against Fethullah Gülen, leader of Fethullah Islamic Movement, for “activities directed toward the establishment of a state based on Islam.” 30 September: Deniz Baykal elected chairman of the Republican People’s Party after a 15-month interval. 4 November: Devlet Bahçeli reelected chairman of the Nationalist Action Party. 24 November: Government privatizes three major state banks—Emlak Bank, Halk Bank, and Ziraat Bank—as part of a plan to withdraw from the financial sector. 27 November: Director of the National Intelligence Agency supports television broadcasts in Kurdish.

2001 1 January: President Ahmet Necdet Sezer says Turkey needs to improve its human rights and democratization record and remove financial irregularities. 21 February: Critical confrontation between President Sezer and Prime Minister Bülent Ecevit leads to the most critical financial crisis during the Republican period. 22 February: Transition to fluctuating rate (within limits) in foreign exchange. 2 March: Kemal Derviş, former deputy director of the World Bank, becomes state minister responsible for the economy. 14 March: New economic program disclosed: the banking sector will be overhauled, interest and foreign exchange rates will be stabilized, and populism will be avoided. 29 April: At the Democratic Left Party Fifth Congress, Ecevit is again elected chairman. 12 May: Parliament passes law to privatize the Telecommunications Agency. 15 May: International Monetary Fund approves augmentation of Turkey’s standby credit to $19 billion. 26 June: Constitutional Court closes the VP on the grounds that it acted against the secular premises of the republic. 11 July: Macedonia and Turkey sign cooperation agreement. 18 July: European Human Rights Court condemns Turkey to pay 270,000 francs as compensation for death under custody. 14 August: Justice and Development Party (JDP) formed under the leadership of former mayor of Istanbul Recep Tayyip Erdoğan. 29 August: Süreyya Ayhan wins gold medal at women’s racing finals in China. September: United Nations agrees to pay $176,300,000 to BOTAŞ for its losses in Gulf War. 16 October: United States announces that Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) and Revolutionary People’s Liberation Party-Front (DHKP-C) are “international terrorist organizations.” 20 October: Abdi İpekçi Friendship and Peace prize given to the Turkish and Greek ministers of agriculture. 12 November: Socialist Workers’ Party officially changes its name to Turkish Communist Party. World Bank elevates Turkey from “middle income” to “high middle income” state status; International Labor Organization depicts Turkey as a “developed” country. 15 December: European Investment Bank extends 185 million euro credits.

2002 6 March: Former chair of the Welfare Party Necmettin Erbakan is condemned to imprisonment for forgery in financial scam. 24 May: Murat Karayalçın founds the Social Democratic People’s Party. 3 August: Capital punishment abrogated by legislation, except in cases of war or threat of war. 22 August: Orhan Pamuk’s novel My Name Is Red selected as the best foreign novel in France. 13 December: Parliament ratifies constitutional amendments to facilitate Recep Tayyip Erdoğan’s election as member of Parliament.

2003 1 March: Parliament rejects resolution to deploy U.S. troops on Turkish soil for attack on Iraq. 9 March: Justice and Development Party leader Recep Tayyip Erdoğan elected as a member of Parliament from Siirt. 13 March: Constitutional Court bans People’s Democracy Party. 11 May: Recai Kutan elected chairman of Felicity Party at its first convention. 17 May: Prime Minister Erdoğan announces Greek Cypriots may visit Turkey visa free. 20 May: Orhan Pamuk receives one of the most prestigious literature prizes in the world, Impac-Dublin, for his novel My Name Is Red. 25 May: Turkey takes first place in 48th Eurovision song contest. 7 October: Resolution to send Turkish soldiers to Iraq rejected in Parliament. 15 November: Bomb attacks on two synagogues in Istanbul, Neve Shalom and Beth Israel.

2004 7 January: United States begins to utilize the İncirlik Air Base as transit point for rotation of soldiers in Iraq. 9 March : Bomb explosions at Istanbul-Kartal Masonic Lodge. 24 March: Court in Şanlıurfa denies applications to change names to Kurdish because the Turkish alphabet does not contain the letters Q, W, or X. 24 April: United Nations secretary-general Kofi Annan’s plan for a resolution to the Cyprus problem welcomed by the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus; South Cyprus rejects the plan. 21 May: State Security Courts abolished. 7 June: First broadcast in the mother tongue made in Bosnian. 17 August: Ambassador Yiğit Alpogan appointed as the first civilian secretary-general of the National Security Council. 17 December: Fatih Akın’s movie Against the Wall wins European best movie award.

2005 1 January: Six zeros dropped from Turkish currency. 19 January: London Royal Academy of Arts hosts exhibition “Turkey: A Thousand Years’ Journey, 600–1600.” 16 February: Feridun Zaimoğlu awarded German Adelbert von Chamisso literature prize. 4 May: Flutist Şefika Kutluer awarded the golden CD of major Swiss recording firms, VDE-GALLO. 20 May: Orhan Pamuk elected honorary member of the American Academy of Arts and Literature. 7 June: Minister of education announces extension of lyceé education from three to four years. 20 June: Metin Kaplan, leader of the Islamic Union Associations in Germany, sentenced to life imprisonment after being deported from Germany for terrorism charges. 22 June: Pamuk awarded peace prize by German Publishers’ Union. 20 July: Labor Party chairman Doğu Perinçek taken into custody in Switzerland for stating that claims of Armenian genocide are an international falsity. 25 July: Tülay Tuğcu elected chair of Constitutional Court to serve as its first female chair. 24 September: Controversial conference on “Ottoman Armenians during the Last Phase of Empire: Scientific Responsibility and Problems of Democracy” takes place at Istanbul Bilgi University. 3 October: European Union Intergovernmental Conference opens for accession negotiations with Turkey. 7 November: Pamuk wins Le Prix Médicis Étranger for his novel Snow.

2006 5 February: Priest Andrea Santore of the Santa Maria Catholic Church in Trabzon murdered. 14 February: European Human Rights Court upholds Turkey’s decision to ban head scarves at universities. 16 February: Political Bureau chief of Hamas, Haled Mashal, arrives in Turkey for talks. 7 March: Communications Regulatory Agency facilitates broadcasts in various Kurdish languages/dialects in radio and television stations of Diyarbakır and Şanlıurfa. 23 March: Broadcasts in Kurdish begin on private radio and television channels. 11 April: United Nations Committee on Discrimination against Women rejects application regarding dismissal from university for wearing a head scarf. 26 April: Iraq extends a protest note to Turkey for deploying military forces on the border to prevent terrorist infiltration into Turkey. 17 May: An armed attack on the Council of State results in one judge dead and four members wounded. 23 May: Greek and Turkish F-16s collide over the Aegean airspace. 8 June: Second Turkish-Arab Economic Forum begins in Istanbul. 26 June: European Union Commission agrees to extend 130 million euros in aid to the Northern Republic of Cyprus and establish a bureau in the area. 13 July: The Baku–Tbilisi–Ceyhan oil pipeline officially becomes operational. 7 August: Turkey extends $1.2 million in humanitarian aid to Lebanon. 8 August: King Saud of Saudi Arabia visits Turkey and signs six agreements. 25 August: British Parliament votes to ban Kurdistan Workers’ Party (PKK) and its sideline associations. 5 September: Turkey’s Parliament ratifies proposal to send military contingency to Lebanon by 340 votes against 192. 3 October: Turkish Airlines flight to Tirana is hijacked to Italy; terrorist gives himself up. 12 October: Nobel Prize for Literature awarded to Orhan Pamuk. Constitutional amendment passes to decrease age for election to Parliament from 30 to 25. 20 October: Amnesty International announces that French law criminalizing denial of Armenian genocide is against freedom of expression. 16 November: United Nations secretary-general Kofi Annan invites by letter presidents of the two Cypriot states to commence talks. 27 November: German chancellor Angela Merkel states “privileged partnership” status of Turkey to European Union is appropriate. 29 November: European Union Commission indefinitely postpones eight accession negotiation articles.

2007 19 January: Editor of weekly Agos newspaper, Hrant Dink, assassinated in Istanbul. 24 January: Some 100,000 people attend Dink’s funeral. 29 January: Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdoğan pledges $2 million in aid to Africa in fight against hunger and AIDS. 31 January: Armenian genocide resolution reaches U.S. House of Representatives. 7 February: Agreement for construction of Kars–Tbilisi–Baku railway signed in Tbilisi. 13 March: Minister of national defense states that Turkey will not participate in the U.S. missile shield project. 14 April: “Republican demonstrations” protest government and uphold secularism. 24 April: Minister of Foreign Affairs Abdullah Gül makes application to Parliament as presidential candidate. 1 May: Constitutional Court denounces the first round of voting in the Parliament for president as unconstitutional. 9 May: Foreign Minister Gül withdraws as candidate for president. 11 May: Constitutional amendment to facilitate presidential elections by national vote accepted in Parliament. 23 May: France’s European Union (EU) minister, Jean-Pierre Jouyet, lends support to Merkel’s proposal for Turkey’s “privileged partnership” with EU. 22 July: Justice and Development Party wins the general elections by 46 percent of nationwide vote. The elections bring 23 Kurds to Parliament as members of Democratic Society Party and end more than 10 years of Kurdish exclusion from Parliament. 28 August: Abdullah Gül, who served as prime minister from 2002 to 2003 and as foreign minister from 2003 to 2007, is elected by Parliament as 11th president of Turkey. 10 September: French president Nicholas Sarkozy announces his stance against Turkey’s full membership in the EU: “privileged partnership.” 19 September: Turkish court blocks all access to YouTube for sharing videos insulting Mustafa Kemal Atatürk, President Gül, Prime Minister Erdoğan, and Turkish army. 11 October: Turkey temporarily recalls its ambassador to the United States, Nabi Şensoy, due to U.S. House Foreign Affairs Committee’s approval of labeling the killings of ethnic Armenians by the Ottoman Empire during World War I as genocide. 17 October: Turkish Parliament approves a motion that allows Turkish troops to cross the border into northern Iraq in its fight with PKK. 20 October: PKK ambushes military convoy, killing 12 soldiers and wounding 16. 11 November: Israel’s president, Shimon Peres, visits Ankara and is conferred an honorary degree. 18 November: Turkey–Greece natural gas pipeline interconnector inaugurated. 29 November: Answering a Spanish journalist’s question on the head scarf ban at universities, Prime Minister Erdoğan says, “So what if it is a political symbol,” and starts one of the most heated controversies by following up with an amendment to the constitution. 2 December: Germany’s chancellor, Angela Merkel, reiterates privileged partnership for Turkey’s association with the EU. 4 December: United Nations secretary-general Ban Ki-moon states no progress in Cyprus talks. 19 December: Armenian Parliament spokesman rejects Turkey’s preconditions to normalize relations. 20 December: Earthquake in Ankara’s Bala province of 5.7 on the Richter scale; no loss of life. 29 December: General Staff announces Greek air force thrice impeded Turkish air force training in international airspace over Aegean Sea.

2008 16 January: President Abdullah Gül inaugurates Turkish industrial zone in Cairo. 20 January: Turkish court bans the website YouTube under a court order issued in response to videos for allegedly insulting Mustafa Kemal Atatürk, considered the father of modern Turkey. 1 February: Constitutional Committee of Parliament approves amendment to constitution to allow head scarves at universities; Interuniversity Council denounces the decision as damaging secularism. 2 February: In Ankara, more than 100,000 people stage protest against the constitutional amendment to lift the ban on head scarves in universities. 9 February: Parliament approves lifting ban on head scarves at universities. 17–18 February: Turkey joins Albania, France, Great Britain, and the United States in recognizing independent Kosovo. 21 February: Turkish Parliament passes a law that restores all state-confiscated properties back to non-Muslim minority owners. 22 February: President Gül signs constitutional amendment to lift the ban on head scarves at universities. 1 March: Professor İlber Ortaylı, poet Ataol Behramoğlu, and director of the Russian Federation-Turkey Research Center, Hasan Aksay, receive the Pushkin Award from the Russian Federation. 4 March: Following the European Human Rights Court decision, Turkey’s Council of State upholds that compulsory religious courses at schools are unlawful. 7 March: Constitutional Court agrees to consider the case against freedom to wear head scarves at universities. 8 March: Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdoğan recommends Turkish women bear at least three children. 12 March: Justice and Development Party (JDP) government announces that it plans to invest more than $12 billion in projects in southeastern Turkey. 15 March: Chief public prosecutor prepares indictment to annul JDP and ban its leadership cadres from active politics on the grounds that they have a hidden agenda of bringing back a state based on Islam. 4 April: Turkey and Israel sign agreement to reciprocally train fresh diplomats. 8 April: In its 2008 report, the European Union (EU) Police Union (EUROPOL) announces the classification of the PKK as a terrorist organization. 11 April: Head of the European Union Commission, Jose Manuel Barraso, says, “Turkey constitutes a strong alternative to political Islam.” 12 April: Directorate of Religious Affairs affiliated to Prime Ministry says it has set aside funds for all categories of religious temples in the country—churches, mosques, synagogues, and so forth. 1 May: May Day demonstrators clash with riot police in Istanbul’s Taksim Square. 2 May: EU Enlargement Commissioner Olli Rehn observes that in Turkey there is a competition between two visions of the future, those of “secularists” and those of “democratic Muslims.” 5 May: Constitutional Court annuls the constitutional amendment that allowed female students wearing head scarves to attend universities. 8 May: Freedom House categorizes Turkey as a “partially free” country, while indicating that the country is nevertheless making further progress toward a more liberal society and polity. 13 May: Britain’s Queen Elizabeth II arrives in Turkey for a three-day state visit. 16 May: Russian Federation accuses Bulgaria, the Czech Republic, Turkey, and United States of providing weapons to Georgia, thus destabilizing the Caucasus. Renate Sommer, member of the European Parliament, points out that Turkey’s accession to the EU is an open-ended process. 2 July: Twenty-one high-profile journalists and political figures imprisoned under the Ergenekon court case that began in July 2007. Ergenekon is alleged to be a nationalist terrorist organization and a faction of the deep state, determined to overthrow JDP government. 9 July: United States Consulate in Istanbul is attacked by three unidentified gunmen. 25 July: Istanbul criminal court agrees to hear the case of the Ergenekon terrorist organization. 30 July: Turkish Constitutional Court decides by a vote of six to five that JDP will not be banned for supporting an Islamic agenda but will be fined half of its annual treasury funding for attempting to annul head scarf ban. 4 October: Turkish military clashes with PKK terrorists in the southeastern province of Hakkari; 15 soldiers and 23 PKK terrorists die. 17 October: Turkey wins balloting for a two-year stint on the UN’s Security Council. 20 October: Trial for the so-called Ergenekon terrorist organization case begins. Eighty-six defendants, including prominent academics, journalists, politicians, retired officers, and union leaders, are accused of belonging to a clandestine ultranationalist organization that aims to overthrow the elected JDP government. 16 December: Over 200 Turkish intellectuals initiate an online petition apologizing for the “great catastrophe” that befell Armenians in the Ottoman Empire during World War I. 30 December: Turkish Radio and Television Agency (TRT) starts broadcasting in Kurdish.

2009 5 January: Nazım Hikmet, declared persona non grata for his Marxist views, regains Turkish citizenship 45 years after his death. 13 January: All but one of the pro-Kurdish Democratic Society Party’s 21 deputies is in jeopardy of losing their parliamentary immunity for violating the Political Parties Law that bans the use of Kurdish language on election campaigns. 29 January: Turkish court annuls prime minister’s ability to manage intelligence services’ wiretapping, returning the power to authorize wiretapping to Turkish courts. 30 January: Prime Minister Recep Tayyip Erdoğan marches off the stage in the Gaza Row at the World Economic Forum in Davos as a reaction to Israeli president Perez’s harsh speech and the moderator’s giving longer time to Perez. 5 February: Kyoto Protocol, an anti–global warming measure, approved in Turkish Parliament. 9 February: Turkey’s Supreme Election Board bans the use of charity for election campaigns. 19 February: Turkish government fines Doğan Media Group, one of the leading media organizations in Turkey, 826 million TL for tax irregularities. The fine is the highest amount of its kind in the history of the Turkish press. 24 February: Turkish state television cuts off its live broadcast of a parliamentary session when Democratic Society Party leader Ahmet Türk continues his speech in Kurdish. 26 February: Turkish Airlines plane crashes near Amsterdam’s Schiphol airport due to a faulty radio altimeter. 27 February: Türkan Saylan, the president of the Association for Supporting Contemporary Life [Çağdaş Yaşamı Destekleme Derneği], is awarded the Vehbi Koç Prize by the Vehbi Koç Foundation. Saylan decides to use the $100,000 for the education of girls. 13 March: Turkish State Railways inaugurates Turkey’s first high-speed rail service on a 200-kilometer system linking the cities of Ankara and Eskişehir. 21 March: A new Turkish television station for Turkic countries of the former Soviet Union launched. 13 April: Former premier and political party leader Necmettin Erbakan, formerly ousted in a bloodless postmodern coup, becomes the chair of the Felicity Party. 30 April: The JDP government announces a constitutional amendment to make it more difficult to shut down political parties. 3 May: Prime Minister Ahmet Davutoğlu emphasizes New Ottomanism. He states Turkey does not belong to one region; Turkey is a Balkan country, Black Sea country, Caucasian, Middle Eastern, Caspian and Gulf region country. Command of the counterpiracy fleet in the Gulf of Aden is transferred from the United States to the Turkish navy. 17 May: Around 20,000 people gather in Ankara to protest JDP government for the investigations and prosecutions of the so-called Ergenekon terrorist organization and the alleged antisecularist nature of the party. 24 May: Monastery of St. Gabriel in the southeastern town of Midyat (Mardin) wins the court case against the villagers who had claimed territory from the monastery. 5 June: Marrying a Turkish citizen will no longer immediately enable one to obtain Turkish citizenship; rather, living in Turkey for a certain period of time, speaking Turkish, and being in good health will be the new criteria. 18 June: An investigation starts in relation to the “Plan to Efface Justice and Development Party and Gülen Movement,” alleged to have been prepared by the General Staff. 26 June: With a view to the EU standards, Parliament passes a law that brings trial of military personnel under civilian courts. 30 June: İlker Başbuğ, chief of General Staff, states that the document named “Fight against Political Reactionism” has not been penned by the military. 3 July: Germany signs an agreement with Turkey to build six submarines for the Turkish navy. 9 July: Chief Prosecutor Sabih Kanadoğlu brings a closure case against the JDP on the grounds that the party had not followed court warnings. Constitutional Court rejects the case. 18 July: Turkey extends smoking ban to all bars, cafes, and restaurants. 30 July: Beşir Atalay, minister of interior affairs, states that the peace process regarding Kurds targets democratization and calls for the participation of intellectuals and the media in the process. 7 August: Russian Federation and Turkey sign an agreement that allows construction of a Russian Federation gas pipeline that will pass through the Turkish portion of the Black Sea. 14 August: Prime Minister Erdoğan states that they have started the democratic opening process. He says, “We love Kurd, Laz, and Turk for the love of Allah.” 17 August: Devlet Bahçeli, leader of Nationalist Action Party (NAP), criticizes the democratic opening project by pointing out that they will not accept a divided Turkey. 31 August: Developments in biotechnology research in Turkey are found valuable by Nature Genetics and Biotechnology Journal. Biotechnology Journal refers to Turkey as a developed country in genetics research. 13 September: Fatih Akın’s movie Soul Kitchen is granted the Special Jury Prize at the 66th Venice Film Festival. 1 October: First Islamic Clothes Fashion and Accessories Fair opens in Istanbul. 4 October: President Gül and Haydar Aliyev, president of Azerbaijan, meet. Turkey guarantees that Turkey’s protocol with Armenia will not be ratified before the Nagorno-Karabakh issue between Armenia and Azerbaijan is settled. 13 October: Turkey signs an agreement with Italy and Russian Federation to build Samsun–Ceyhan oil pipeline known as the Trans-Anatolian Pipeline. 16 October: The president of the Union of Chambers and Commodity Exchanges of Turkey [Türkiye Odalar ve Borsalar Birliği—TOBB], Rıfat Hisarcıklıoğlu, elected as the deputy president of the European Association of Chambers of Commerce and Industry. 19 October: Turkey and Qatar lift mutual visa requirements. 20 October: Turkey signs 48 agreements with Iraq to improve relations between the two nations. 22 October: Turkey’s ranking drops to 122 in 2009 Press Freedom Index. Turkish state is criticized for its far too frequent resort to Article 301 in the Penal Law that makes possible the prosecution of any statement that criticizes Turkish identity. 3 November: Turkey and Israel conduct joint search-and-rescue exercises for the first time since Israel was excluded from North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) military exercises. 13 November: Turkey introduces new reforms to increase the rights of its Kurdish population as part of the democratic opening process, such as fewer restrictions on the Kurdish language and the establishment of a special commission to investigate allegations of torture and abuse. 25 November: Libya and Turkey sign a series of agreements to improve bilateral relations. Among them is one that lifts visa restrictions between the two countries. 6 December: Prime Minister Erdoğan states that Turkey will not send additional troops to Afghanistan despite the fact that there is a demand from the United States. 8 December: Prime Minister Erdoğan meets U.S. president Barack Obama at Washington. They decide to increase American-Turkish cooperation in various fields from science and art to politics and technology. 11 December: Turkey’s Constitutional Court bans the pro-Kurdish Democratic Society Party with the reason that the party has links to the PKK terrorist organization. Prime Minister Erdoğan criticizes the court’s decision, stating that it contravenes government’s efforts to improve Kurdish rights and constitutes a setback for the efforts to improve Turkish-Kurdish relations.

2010 14 January: Russian Federation and Turkey sign an agreement for the construction of Turkey’s first nuclear plant. 3 February: European Court of Human Rights decides that expression of religion on ID cards in Turkey is against Article 9 of the European Convention on Human Rights. 16 February: European Court of Human Rights rules against Turkey’s decision to ban Guillaume Apollinaire’s erotic novel The Eleven Thousand Rods. The court states that banning the book hinders public access to the European literary heritage and is a violation of Article 10 of the European Convention of Human Rights about the freedom of expression. 19 February: Service held by the Armenian patriarchate of Istanbul at the Armenian Cathedral Church of the Holy Cross in Lake Van 95 years after the last one. 21 February: The film Honey [Bal] by the director Semih Kaplanoğlu is awarded the Golden Bear at the 60th Berlin International Film Festival. 8 April: Greece and Turkey sign a series of measures to strengthen ties between their militaries with the aim of overcoming their long-standing rivalry. 22 April: Human Rights Watch issues a report on police abuse in Turkey, citing violence against children and excessive use of lethal force. 24 April: For the first time in Turkey, protestors comprising different ethnic and religious groups openly commemorate the 95th anniversary of the 1915–1917 mass killings of Armenians. 13 May: Mersin Akkuyu Nuclear Plant Agreement and the agreement for visa-free travel between Russian Federation and Turkey signed. 31 May: Israel attacks in international waters the Blue Marmara [Mavi Marmara], one of the ships in the aid flotilla heading toward Gaza Strip. 22 June: Southeast European Cooperation Process (SEECP) takes place in Istanbul. 28 June: Following Israel’s raid on the aid flotilla in Gaza, Turkey decides to close its airspace to noncivilian Israeli aircraft. 12 July: In a private meeting with U.S. secretary of state Hillary Clinton, Turkish foreign minister Ahmet Davutoğlu states that Turkey will not take part in international efforts regarding Iran’s nuclear program. 19 July: U.S. senator John McCain says that by maintaining the secular and democratic heritage of Atatürk, Turkey will effectively fight against the increase of radical Islam in the region. 1 August: Turkish female athlete Nevin Yanıt wins gold medal for women’s 100-meter hurdles final at the 20th European Athletics Championships in Barcelona. 12 September: Turkey holds referendum for constitutional change package. The amendments are approved. 21 September: The nephews of Archbishop Aram Ateşyan, general vicar of the Armenian patriarch in Turkey, change their identity from Muslim to Christian. 5 October: Turkish director Fatih Akın honored with the order of merit by Christian Wolff, president of Germany, for his contributions in the field of culture in Germany. 19 October: First Turkish-German University groundbreaking ceremony takes place in Istanbul. 28 October: At the National Security Council meeting, reactionism [irtica] is no longer considered a domestic security issue. 29 November: Deed of the Greek orphanage on Büyükada, the largest of Prince Islands in the Marmara Sea, transferred to the Orthodox patriarchate in Istanbul.

2011 22 January: Ankara University Stem Cell Institute produces muscle from stem cell, the first of its kind in the world. 28 January: Official ceremony organized for the first time in Neve Shalom Synagogue in Istanbul for victims of the Holocaust. 17 March: Moscow State Diplomacy Institute confers on Erdoğan honorary Ph.D. degree. 28 March: Turkish prime minister Erdoğan meets with Syrian president Bashar al-Assad, encouraging him to pay attention to his people’s call for reforms. 12 June: General elections held. Ruling JDP garners 50 percent of votes and 327 seats in Parliament while Republican People’s Party (RPP) gets 21 percent of votes and 135 seats and Nationalist Action Party (NAP) gathers 14 percent of votes and 53 seats. Thirty-six pro-Kurdish Peace and Democracy Party (PDP) independent candidates enter Parliament. 17 June: Hollywood star and UN High Commissioner for Refugees (UNHCR) goodwill ambassador Angelina Jolie visits Syrian refugee camp in the city of Hatay. 4 August: Turkey refuses to participate in joint naval exercises with the United States and Israel in the Mediterranean. 1 September: Children who hold Armenian citizenship can now attend Armenian community schools in Turkey. 2 September: Turkey declines its diplomatic relations and suspends military cooperation with Israel following Israel’s refusal to apologize for the Mavi Marmara incident. 21 October: Temple in Loedikya, ancient city in Denizli, believed to be one of the seven holy churches, discovered. 23 November: Prime Minister Erdoğan makes an apology for Turkish military’s killing of more than 13,000 Kurds in the 1930s, being the first Turkish prime minister to do so. 2 December: Science Academy [Bilim Akademisi] formed. 15 December: İzmir Jewish Community granted the status of foundation after more than 100 years. 22 December: French National Assembly passes a bill criminalizing the denial that the mass killing of Armenians at the end of World War I was genocide. 27 December: Turkey signs a $5 billion agreement with Azerbaijan on the Trans-Anatolian Natural Gas Pipeline. 28 December: Turkey signs an agreement with Russian Federation regarding the South Stream natural gas pipeline to Europe through Turkish territorial waters.

2012 5 January: Former chief of General Staff General İlker Başbuğ is arrested by a civilian court on charges of his relationship with so-called Ergenekon terrorist organization alleged to have made plans to overthrow the government by force. 19 January: Ten thousand people march silently in Istanbul at the fifth anniversary of the murder of Hrant Dink, Turkish journalist of Armenian descent. 8 March: Turkish Parliament passes a bill to prevent violence against women and to increase assistance for victims. 10 April: China and Turkey sign two nuclear agreements. 12 April: Minister of Education Ömer Dinçer announces that wearing of head scarf at secondary and high schools will be permitted in elective course classes. 20 April: President of Iraqi Kurdistan region Mesud Barzani and Prime Minister Erdoğan discuss the issues of Iraq, Syria, and terrorism. 28 April: First full face transplant in Turkey is performed for 19-year-old Uğur Acar. 5 May: Law of reciprocity, which allows the selling of real estate to citizens of 62 countries, is adopted. 21 May: Circassians in Turkey raise demands for education in their mother tongue and TV and radio broadcasting in Circassian. 23 June: Göksu/Panayia holy spring is returned to the foundation of Kandilli Metamorphosis Church. 10 July: Turkish novelist Elif Şafak is awarded Chevalier dans l’Ordre des Arts et des Lettres by France for her intellectual contribution to freedom of expression, intercultural dialogue, and human rights. 29 July: New sculpture belonging to a Hittite king dating back to 1000 B.C.E. discovered. 8 August: Number of Syrian refugees taking shelter in Turkey reaches almost 50,000. 2 October: Remains of former president Turgut Özal will be exhumed due to allegations that he was poisoned. 5 October: Resolution for sending troops to other countries is approved in Parliament, particularly for sending troops to Syria. 14 October: First pipe of the underwater pipeline project for water transfer from Turkey to the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus placed in the Mediterranean. 28 November: Dress code for precollege schools changes: students of primary, elementary, and high schools will no longer be forced to wear one style of school uniforms. 14 December: United States signs a deployment order that sends 400 U.S. troops and two batteries of Patriot missiles to Turkey against possible missile attacks from Syria.

2013 8 January: Turkish Bank Ziraat has opened branches in Greece. 21 January: First of six NATO Patriot missile batteries intended to protect Turkey from potential missile attacks from Syria arrives at İskenderun port. 22 February: Nationwide survey demonstrates that 95 percent of participants believe that Turkish and Kurdish people will continue to live together in Turkey. In the same survey, 51 percent of participants support negotiations with jailed terrorist leader Abdullah Öcalan, and 65 percent support the peace process. 1 March: Turkish prime minister Erdoğan states at a UN meeting in Vienna that Zionism is a crime against humanity. Israeli prime minister Benjamin Netanyahu says Erdoğan’s statement is false. 19 March: Attorney of the Ergenekon court case demands lifetime imprisonment for retired general İlker Başbuğ, who was the 26th chief of General Staff with the allegation that he was the leader of the Ergenekon terrorist organization. 21 March: Newroz is celebrated peacefully in Diyarbakır with a large crowd. Terrorist leader Öcalan’s message delivered in Kurdish and Turkish by PDP deputies. 23 March: Turkish prime minister Erdoğan accepts Israeli prime minister Benjamin Netanyahu’s apology for Israel’s raid on the Turkish aid flotilla on its way to Gaza in 2010. 24 March: Prime Minister Erdoğan states that there will be a seven-member wise people commission, comprising academics and representatives from the private sector, media, and civil society organizations. 9 April: Turkish Foreign Ministry announces that two new refugee camps will be set up in the southeastern town of Midyat (Mardin) for Assyrian Christians and Kurds from Syria. 24 May: A new law bans advertising alcohol and prohibits shops from selling alcohol from 10 p.m. to 6 a.m. 29 May: Protestors who have been keeping watch against construction of a shopping mall in Gezi Park clash with police. Some deputies from PDP and Republican People’s Party (RPP), as well as journalists, actors, and actresses, join protestors in their wish to save the park. 2 June: Gezi Park protests spread all over Turkey. 15 June: Prime Minister Erdoğan states that the government will suspend plans for Gezi Park until a court decision is made. 3 July: Constitutional Court opens the way for individual applications regarding long detention periods and the right to a fair trial before the trial is finalized. 6 August: Ergenekon court case is finalized after four years and 10 months. The 21 suspects are acquitted, the remaining 254 being handed different prison sentences. Nine suspects, including retired general Veli Küçük, journalist Tuncay Özkan, president of Labor Party Doğu Perinçek, and retired colonel Dursun Çiçek, are given aggravated life imprisonment; and 10 suspects, including retired general and chief of General Staff İlker Başbuğ, retired general Hurşit Tolon, retired general Şener Eruygur, and press agent of Turkish Orthodox patriarchate Sevgi Erenerol, are given life imprisonment. 16 September: The Greek primary school on Gökçeada (Imbros) restarts education after 49 years. 1 October: Prime Minister Erdoğan introduces democratization package. The package includes free usage of letters x, w, and q, which are in the Kurdish alphabet, and of the pre-1980 names of villages; abandonment of the practice of jointly reading the national oath at primary schools every morning; and letting public servants, including teachers, doctors, and parliamentarians, put on head scarves, depending on their free will. 31 October: Excavations on the European side of Istanbul reveal the first signs of Hittites’ existence in the region. The ruins are estimated to be 3,800 years old. 1 November: First parliamentarians with head scarves appear in Parliament. 16 December: Agreements to start visa-free EU travel for Turkish citizens signed in Ankara. 17 December: Eighty-four people are taken into custody under the operation of “Grand Bribery.” Allegations include the sons of minister for interior affairs Muhammer Güler, economy minister Zafer Çağlayan, and minister of environment Erdoğan Bayraktar. Prime Minister Erdoğan says that the secret organization that acts like a state within the state should be revealed.

2014 8 January: Chief of General Staff Necdet Özel states that it is not possible anymore to have military tutelage. 1 March: Prime Minister Erdoğan calls out to Fethullah Gülen, who has been living in the United States and demands Gülen’s return to Turkey to enter active politics instead of organizing opposition from the United States. He states that Gülen has been involved in activities against Turkey’s national security. He states that earlier Gülen was a peaceful, pious person, but later he was induced to capture the state from within. 8 March: Former chief of General Staff İlker Başbuğ, earlier given a life sentence, released. 30 March: Turkey holds local elections. JDP wins elections in 17 metropolitan cities including Ankara and Istanbul and 31 other cities. 23 April: For the first time in the history of the Turkish Republic, the Prime Ministry makes an official statement about the 1915 events. Prime Minister Erdoğan states that “the incidents that had taken place are common pains of all of us. Sharing and understanding the pain of Armenians and their commemoration of memories is a duty for humanity.” Armenian patriarch agent-general welcomes Erdoğan’s statements and expresses that his words soothe Armenians’ feelings. 15 May: Fire starts in mine in Soma (Manisa); 301 miners lose their lives. 1 August: Council of Europe Convention on Preventing and Combating Violence against Women and Domestic Violence, commonly known as the Istanbul Convention, signed by 10 European states and Turkey in 2011, comes into force. 10 August: Prime Minister Erdoğan becomes Turkey’s first popularly elected president. 15 August: Fifth Virgin Mary rite is held under the leadership of Greek Orthodox patriarch Dimitris Bartholomeus in the historic Sumela Monastery on the Black Sea coast. The patriarch delivers a message for global peace. 28 August: Erdoğan sworn in in front of the Turkish Parliament as Turkey’s new president for a five-year term. Many consider Erdoğan to be the most powerful political figure in Turkish politics since the first president of Turkey, Mustafa Kemal Atatürk. 8 September: According to official data, in the last three years at least 30,000 Syrian children have been born in Turkey in the provinces with refugee camps. 22 September: Deputy Prime Minister Numan Kurtulmuş announces that more than 130,000 Syrians have fled to Turkey in the past days. Turkey has received more than one million refugees since the beginning of the Syrian conflict. 28 September: Ministry of Education forbids students having tattoos or piercings. 29 September: Because of ISIS attacks on Kobani (Syria), more than 150,000 Syrian Kurds have fled into Turkey. 2 October: Turkish Parliament passes resolution that allows military action in Syria and Iraq and also foreign troops to launch attacks from Turkish territory. 8 October: At least 23 people die in the two-day-long demonstrations across Turkey as Kurdish protestors demand the government take action to protect Kobani from ISIS attacks. 20 October: Minister of Foreign Affairs Mevlüt Çavuşoğlu announces that Turkey will allow Kurdish peshmerga to cross into Syria to help fight against ISIS attacks. Turkey’s decision is also welcomed by the international community. 1 December: Papa Francesco visits Turkey. 3 December: Turkish Parliament passes bill that tightens government’s control over the judiciary and gives police greater powers to conduct searches. 8 December: President Erdoğan announces plans to introduce mandatory Ottoman Turkish lessons in public school curriculum. 29 December: Turkey provides identification cards for Syrian refugees that provide access to public housing, education, health care, and other social programs. This constitutes an important move by the government, since Syrians who fled to Turkey are not given official refugee status.

2015 20 January: President Erdoğan states that his phone was illegally wiretapped last year during a corruption scandal. He also accuses Fethullah Gülen, self-exiled cleric in the United States, of supporting the wiretappers. 5 February: Bank Asya, which is affiliated with self-exiled cleric Gülen, is taken over by the government. Banking regulators state that the bank has not been transparent in its business. 21 February: Turkish army conducts mission into Syria to save the Tomb of Suleiman Shah, a 13th-century ancestor of the Ottoman Empire. The tomb has been under ISIS siege. 7 June: General elections are held. The ruling JDP loses its parliamentary majority for the first time in its history. The left-leaning pro-Kurdish Peoples’ Democratic Party (PDP) passes the threshold and gains seats. Since no party holds a majority to form the government, talks commence for possible government coalition. August: Far leftist terrorist group DHKP-C attacks U.S. consulate in Istanbul with gunfire. No one injured. 18 August: Negotiations for coalition government fail, triggering snap polls in November. 2 September: Image of drowned three-year-old Syrian boy Alan Kurdi on a popular tourist beach increases public and international attention to the humanitarian crisis of refugees who are attempting to cross into Europe by illegal means. 10 October: Peace rally in Ankara attacked by two suicide bombings; 102 people lose their lives while more than 250 are wounded. The attack is believed to be organized by ISIS. 31 October: Turkish military attacks ISIS targets after the chief prosecutor’s announcement that they have strong evidence for ISIS responsibility for Ankara suicide bombing at the train station. 1 November: General elections are held since no coalition government could be formed after 7 June elections. JDP increases its share of votes to 49 percent, which brings it the majority in Parliament with 317 seats. 15 November: Turkey hosts annual summit of Group of Twenty (G20) in Antalya. 17 November: Turkey abandons deal with China to develop missile defense system. The prospect of such a deal had caused concerns in NATO. 24 November: Turkey shoots down Russian Federation warplane that violated Turkish airspace. The pilot of the warplane dies. 27 November: Thousands of people gather in Istanbul to protest the arrest of journalist Can Dündar, editor in chief of one of the opposition newspapers, Republic [Cumhuriyet], and Erdem Gül, bureau chief of the same newspaper. Journalists are charged with disclosing state secrets. 28 November: Russian Federation introduces sanctions on Turkey after the downing of its warplane on 24 November. Sanctions include restrictions on Turkish labor, imports, and construction projects. Russian Federation also takes steps to reduce number of Russian Federation tourists visiting Turkey. 30 November: Turkey signs agreement with European Union (EU) that grants the country $3.2 billion to support Syrian refugees and improve their living conditions. The agreement also includes political concessions for visa-free travel for Turkish citizens within the EU.

2016 15 January: Police detain 27 academics for signing petition titled “We Will Not Be a Part of This Crime,” which is alleged as disseminating terrorist propaganda. The petition is also signed by more than 1,000 academics working at Turkish universities and abroad. The detained academics are released the same day. 17 February: Kurdistan Freedom Hawks (TAK), the youth branch of the terrorist organization PKK, conducts a bomb attack on the bus convoy that carries military personnel in Ankara. The bombing kills 28 people and wounds more than 60. President Erdoğan states that the People’s Defense Unit (YPG) has been involved in the bombing. The United States has been supporting YPG in their fight against ISIS in Syria. 4 March: Justice and Development Party (JDP) government takes control of the daily newspaper Time [Zaman], which has been one of the most circulated newspapers in Turkey. The newspaper was an important broadcasting organization of the Fethullah Gülen group, which has been critical of the government and of President Erdoğan. 18 March: Prime Minister Ahmet Davutoğlu and the president of the European Council, Donald Tusk, confirm that European Union (EU) and Turkey have agreed to return all refugees and migrants arriving in Greece to Turkey. In return, EU promises to revisit talks on Turkey’s EU membership and facilitate the expense of funds allocated to help Syrian refugees already in Turkey. Since the outbreak of war in Syria, more than 2.7 million Syrians have arrived in Turkey. 27 April: Galatasaray basketball team wins the Eurocup. 20 May: Turkish Parliament passes the constitutional amendment that divests deputies of their immunity from prosecution. The amendment particularly aims at deputies of the pro-Kurdish Peoples’ Democratic Party (PDP), the third-largest party in Parliament. 2 June: The German parliament recognizes the mass killing of Armenians during the Ottoman Empire at the end of World War I as genocide. Turkey, objecting to the terms “genocide” and “ethnic cleansing,” recalls its ambassador to Berlin. 18 June: London-based Syrian Observatory for Humans Rights (SOHR) states that border guards shot to death eight Syrian refugees who were trying to cross illegally into Turkey. 19 June: Istanbul riot police disperse a transgender pride march on İstiklal Avenue, firing tear gas and rubber pellets. Homosexuality is not an official crime in Turkey, but its practice in public remains controversial among conservative and nationalist groups. 23 June: Turkish Parliament passes a law that obstructs prosecution of soldiers for human rights abuses committed during counterterrorism operations. 26 June: Prime Minister Yıldırım and Israeli prime minister Benjamin Netanyahu announce a deal to reconcile relations between the two countries after a six-year deadlock. They agree on reopening embassies and on $20 million compensation for the families of Turkish activists who lost their lives in the raid on the Mavi Marmara aid flotilla in 2010. 27 June: President Erdoğan apologizes to Russian Federation president Vladimir Putin for downing of the Russian Federation jet in November 2015 near Turkish-Syrian border, killing the pilot of the jet. 1 July: Osmangazi Bridge, which crosses the İzmit Bay, is opened. The bridge is the fourth-longest suspension bridge in the world and the second longest in Europe. 3 July: Turkey sends 11,000 tons of humanitarian aid to Gaza Strip via the Israeli port of Ashdod. Israel agrees to transfer the aid over land due to its blockade of Gaza since 2006. 6 July: Russian Federation officially allows charter flights between Russian Federation and Turkey to resume. Russian Federation has also lifted travel sanctions on tours to Turkey. 7 July: Fifteen-year-old Ayşe Begüm Onbaşı wins gold medal in the Aerobic Gymnastic World Championship. 15 July: Factions of Turkish army controlled by Fethullah Gülen, the self-exiled cleric in the United States, attempt a coup against President Erdoğan and the Justice and Development Party government. They declare martial law via state television channel TRT and seize control of Istanbul Atatürk International Airport and the two Bosporus bridges. On the night of the attempt, they raid Parliament and the surroundings of the Presidential Palace in Beştepe, Ankara. President Erdoğan denounces the attempt via video footage streamed through a news anchor’s mobile phone during a televised broadcast. President Erdoğan calls on the public to take to the streets, which they readily do. Consequently, the coup attempt fails, leaving 265 people dead and at least 1,400 wounded. 21 July: JDP government declares three-month-long state of emergency. 22 July: The date 15 July is declared the Commemoration Day of Martyrs and also an official national holiday. 7 August: Democracy and Martyrs rally is organized and attended by the leaders and supporters of three political parties—JDP, Republican People’s Party (RPP), and Nationalist Action Party (NAP). Five million people are claimed to have participated in the historic rally. 26 August: A third bridge crossing the Bosporus is opened. Yavuz Sultan Selim’s name is given to the bridge despite opposition, particularly from the Alevi people. 8 September: JDP government decides to stay on summer time all year round with the argument that it will bring more use of daylight. 3 October: State of emergency is extended another three months. 4 November: Nine MPs of PDP, including the party’s copresidents Selahattin Demirtaş and Figen Yüksekdağ, are arrested for their alleged links with the PKK terrorist organization. 5 December: Turkey launches the Göktürk-1 satellite to provide high-definition satellite images for civilian and military purposes. 10 December: Twin bomb attacks on police officers take place outside Beşiktaş football stadium in Istanbul at the end of a game. Thirty-eight police officers and eight civilians lose their lives. 18 December: World-renowned Turkish pianist Fazıl Say is awarded the International Beethoven Prize. 19 December: Russian Federation’s ambassador to Turkey, Andrey Karlov, is shot dead by a Turkish police officer in civilian clothes in an art gallery in Ankara.

2017 1 January: ISIS attacks Reina nightclub in Istanbul on New Year’s Eve; 39 people die and 71 are wounded. 4 January: State of emergency is extended another three months. 8 January: Foreign Affairs Minister Mevlüt Çavuşoğlu states that 350 diplomats and 58 civil servants in the ministry were dismissed from their posts for their alleged ties with FETÖ. 12 January: UN secretary-general Antonio Guterres says talks in Geneva to resolve Cyprus issue are close to a settlement. 26 January: Greece refuses to return to Turkey the eight soldiers allegedly affiliated with FETÖ. 28 January: British prime minister Theresa May visits Turkey to meet President Erdoğan. May says Turkey is an important NATO ally and it is important that the country sustains democracy by maintaining rule of law and respect for human rights. 2 February: German prime minister Angela Merkel visits Turkey to meet President Erdoğan. The two leaders discuss the issues of terrorism, refugees, and economic cooperation. 4 February: One hundred pilots of Turkish armed forces are arrested for alleged involvement with the terrorist organization FETÖ; 180 pilots are released for being informants. 5 February: Turkish police arrest 690 suspects in operations for allegedly having ties with ISIS. 7 February: On the same grounds, 4,464 civil servants are dismissed from their posts in public service with Legislative Decree 686. 9 February: U.S. CIA chief Mike Pompeo pays his first foreign visit to Turkey to meet officials and President Erdoğan regarding the issues of Syria, ISIS, and FETÖ. 28 February: Turkey sets up a military base near the strategic Akil Hill in the Syrian city of Al-Bab. 2 March: Germany cancels the speech of Turkish minister of justice Bekir Bozdağ that would have been delivered at the meeting of the Union of European Turkish Democrats. 4 March: State prosecutor demands 2,988 life sentences for 38 military personnel suspected of taking part in the failed coup attempt on 15 July. 8 March: Foreign Affairs Minister Çavuşoğlu’s speech in Hamburg is canceled by Germany for “security reasons.” 10 March President Erdoğan pays a visit to Moscow to meet Russian Federation’s President Vladimir Putin. The two leaders discuss bilateral relations between Russian Federation and Turkey as well as developments in Syria. 11 March: Family and Social Policies Minister Fatma Betül Sayan Kaya is barred in the Netherlands from entering the consulate as part of referendum campaign. The Netherlands also bars Turkish foreign minister Çavuşoğlu from flying to the country. Clashes occur between Turkish protestors and Dutch police. 16 March: Turkish and South Korean firms sign deal for building the world’s longest suspension bridge over the Dardanelles. The bridge is planned to be 1.2 miles long and will cost around $2.8 billion. 26 March: President Erdoğan remarks that Turkey may hold a referendum on the continuation of the European Union (EU) negotiations process. 8 April: Turkey declares its support for U.S. missile strike against Syrian air base in response to Assad’s chemical attack in Syria. 12 April: Public prosecutor demands life imprisonment for 30 journalists of Istanbul daily Time [Zaman] for allegedly being close to FETÖ terrorist organization. Last Ergenekon trial, the OdaTV trial, ends with acquittal of all 13 defendants. 16 April: Turkey votes in constitutional referendum. Constitutional amendments are approved with 51.4 percent yes votes; parliamentary democracy replaced by “presidential government system.” 17 April: State of emergency is extended another three months. 19 April: Supreme Electoral Council refuses applications of RPP, PDP, and Homeland Party for cancellation of the referendum. 25 April: Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of Europe (PACE) votes to reintroduce a monitoring process for Turkey because the constitutional amendments approved in the 16 April referendum do not comply with Europe’s fundamental understanding of democracy. 1 May: The number of academics expelled from universities under the state of emergency regime reaches 5,295. 4 May: Trials of 12 September military coup conclude without any punishment due to the deaths of the last two suspected generals, Kenan Evren and Tahsin Şahinkaya. Iran, Russian Federation, and Turkey sign a memorandum to establish four de-escalation zones in Syria. 9 May: President Erdoğan states that Turkey’s willingness to sustain EU membership process on equal, win-win basis continues. 16 May: President Erdoğan visits White House to meet American president Donald Trump. Trump declares America’s support for Turkey’s fight against terrorist organizations and willingness to cooperate with Turkey for the establishment of peace and security in the Middle East. 21 May: President Erdoğan once again leader of the ruling Justice and Development Party. 22 May: Trial of generals of failed coup attempt starts in Ankara. Prosecutors demand life sentences for each of the 2,988 suspects. June: Son-in-law of Bülent Arınç, one of the founders of JDP, is arrested on charges of being a member of the FETÖ terrorist organization. 6 June: Turkey does not support the sanctions against Qatar imposed by Saudi Arabia, Bahrain, Egypt, and the United Arab Emirates. 8 June: Turkish Parliament approves agreements with Qatar for military cooperation. 12 June: Turkish economy grows 5 percent in the first quarter of 2017. 14 June: Journalist and RPP MP Enis Berberoğlu arrested in relation with the MİT truck case and sentenced to 25 years. RPP leader Kemal Kılıçdaroğlu will start a “Justice March” from Ankara to Istanbul. 15 June: Kılıçdaroğlu’s Justice March begins. Thousands give their support by accompanying him. 18 June: The first group of Turkish soldiers arrives in Qatar to take part in joint military exercises. 19 June: President Erdoğan criticizes Justice March of Kılıçdaroğlu by saying that rule of law should be respected.